Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: The Senate President, the Presiding Officer,
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: and Senator-Judges of the Impeachment Court.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: Sergeant at Arms is directed to make a proclamation.
Alfredo Sotto Corpuz: All persons are commanded to keep silent under pain of penalty while the Impeachment Court is in session for the trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: The Impeachment Trial of Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte is hereby called to order. We shall be led in prayer by Senator Judge Raffy Tulfo.
Sen. Raffy T. Tulfo: Almighty Father, as we enter The seventh week of the impeachment trial guide everyone here. The senator-judges, the presiding officer, the prosecution and defense counsels, the witnesses, and the Filipino people so that we remember why we are conducting these proceedings. Help us to make the most of the Time and resources of our people by making the impeachment trial an instrument that would restore the people's trust in their public officials. Finally, send our most holy spirit upon us so that we are rendered a just judgment over this case. May we embody what Jesus said that for the measure you use, it will be measured to you. Lord, let our words and actions here reflect the public servants that we should be. All these we pray in your mighty name. Amen.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: senator-judge, Marcoleta, senator-judge, Marcos, senator-judge, Padilla, senator-judge, Pangilinan, senator-judge, Soto III, senator-judge, Tulfo Erwin, senator-judge, Tulfo Rafi, senator-judge, Villanueva, senator-judge, Villar Camil, senator-judge, Villar Marc, senator-judge, Zubiri, the presiding officer, senator-judge, Escudero, senate president, senator-judge, Gatchalian.
Sen. Sherwin T. Gatchalian: 13 senator-judges present, the chair declares the presence of a quorum. In accordance with the rules of procedure on impeachment trials, the Chair now recognizes the duly elected presiding officer to preside over the proceedings of the impeachment court.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Mr. Senate President. If there are no objections, we shall dispense with the reading of the August 12, 2026 Journal of the Senate sitting as an impeachment court and shall consider the same as approved.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Clerk of Court is directed to kindly call the case before the impeachment court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Case number 004-2026. In the
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: matter of impeachment trial, Vice President Sara Zimmerman Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Appearances of the parties.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Same appearance for the prosecution, Your Honor. We are ready. Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, Honorable Chua.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Same appearance for the respondent accused, Your Honor. Good morning.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Atty. Powa.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Call your witness, Honorable Chua.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Your Honor, before we call our next witness, Your Honor.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: May we respectfully ask the Honorable Court to recognize Attorney Ligutan, counsel for the prosecution because we understand that his name was alluded to by the defense in the last hearing, Your Honor. May he be given the opportunity to make a brief manifestation or comment. At
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the proper time we will, Honorable Attorney Ligutan. At the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: proper time we will. The Chair does not intend to rule yet on that matter at this time. But before the Chair does so, Attorney Ligutan will be heard. I assure you.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: In that case, Your Honor, may we request the public prosecutor, Congressman Lordan Suwan, be recognized by the Chair for the presentation of our next witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Honorable Suwan is recognized.
Atty. Michael Wesley Poa: Your Honor, on the part of the defense, Your Honor, may we also request that Attorney Lyndon Bacuel be recognized for
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: this witness. Attorney Lyndon, you are recognized, sir, as far as this witness is concerned.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Good morning, Your Honor. Lyndon Bacuel, appearing for respondent accused.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Honorable Suwan is recognized.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Thank you, Your Honor.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: May it please the Honorable Impeachment Court. The prosecution calls Ms. Marivic M. Pareja.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Clerk of Court, through the Sergeant at Arms, is directed to kindly situate Ms. Marivic Pareja to the witness stand.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly place the witness under oath, Clerk of Court.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Please raise your right hand. You, Marivic M. Pareja, do swear... that the evidence you shall give in the case now pending between the Philippines and Vice President Cyrus Zimmerman Duterte shall be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth. So help you God.
Marivic M. Pareja: Yes, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly be seated.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Marivic. Atty. Soan, you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: are recognized to make your offer.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honors, before we proceed with the offer of testimony, we respectfully manifest that we are distributing copies to all the senator-judges. of our offer of testimony. And we also request that this be flashed on the screen for the convenience of the senators and the viewing public.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honor, we only have four offers for the testimony of Witness Pareja, Your Honor.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honor, the testimony of Witness Marivic M. Pareja is being offered to prove the following. Number one, she has been an employee of the House of Representatives for the past 27 years. and has for the last eight years up to the present served as the service director of the Legislative Archives and Museum Management Service or Archives of the House of Representatives. Number two,
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: the Archives is the official repository of all records of the House of Representatives including those that were transmitted to it by the Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability or CGGPA. in connection with the committee's hearings conducted from September 18, 2024 to December 9, 2024 and is responsible for the storage, preservation, retrieval, and release of certified true copies of such records and issuance of certifications.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Number three, the identity of the following documents that were received by the Archives for Storage and Custody. as transmitted by the Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability relative to its September 18, 2024 to December 9, 2024 committee hearings.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honor, may we be allowed to flash on the screen these documents as I am enumerating them?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before you proceed, counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: let
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: me be the one to do it. Would Attorney Lyndon be willing to stipulate? Insofar as the current position of the witness in the house is concerned relative to offers 1 and 2 of the council.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Yes, Your Honor, stipulated.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Second, counsel, the Honorable Suwan, you will only be presenting documents enumerated in your offer, namely P. Roman numeral number 1-26A up to P.R.1-26L1.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May I ask,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: insofar as your pre-marked documents P.R.1-3 up
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: to P.R.1-25I-1, these were not part of the documents you requested this Court to take judicial notice of? which we are more than willing to do because they're of the same nature. And since you're not presenting it to this witness, would you want to make the corresponding motion for us to take judicial notice of those documents? Again, to reiterate, P-RN 1-3 up to P-RN 1-25-I-1.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Mostly, these are documents pertaining to documents submitted to the House. pertaining to the ombudsman case and the counter affidavits of some of the respondents in that case? Yes, Your Honor. Or you'd have no intention of presenting those documents anymore?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: We do, Your Honor, and judicial notice would be much appreciated.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly ask for it because it is not part of those that we can give judicial notice of in a mandatory manner. So you are asking for judicial notice for the documents I mentioned?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Yes, Your Honor, the prosecution moves.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Any objection on the part of the respondent? Again, just as to the existence of these documents, as to the fact that they were submitted before the House of Representatives, not as to the truth or relevance of these documents to these proceedings.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Stipulated, Your Honor. We have no objection as regards the motion to take judicial notice of these documents.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Court therefore makes an order that the documents inclusive from P-RN1-3 to P-RN1-25I-1 are all taken judicial notice of. Copies are therefore directed to be furnished to all the senator-judges for their information and reference. Again, as to the fact that these are part of the official records of the House, duly submitted to them, and that
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: and that they form part of the records forming the House deliberations and hearings. Now, next, Honorable Suwan, insofar as these documents you presented are concerned, again, these are all submissions to the House, correct?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May I hear from Counsel for Respondent, Atty. Linden? Are you willing to stipulate as to these documents that they intend to present through the witness, Atty. Pareja? Again, only as to the fact that they were submitted to the House, part of the official records of the House, and that in the performance of her regular duties that these are within her custody, and that she performed her duties in the regular course of events.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: We stipulate, Your Honor, as regards the transmittal of these documents to the Department of the Witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And that she is in possession and custody of these documents?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: as part of the official records of the hearings of the House.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honorable Suwan, since it has been stipulated by the Council, would there be anything else? Again, just for clarity, Atty. Linden, we are referring to previously
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: marked documents P-R1-26-A up to P-R1-26-L-1. A total of 11 documents, I think you've been furnished with a copy?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: No, Your Honor. We have not... Kindly
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: furnish opposing counsel with a copy.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And it's also being flashed on the screen, counsel.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: If I may, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, Honorable Suwan?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: For the record, may we be allowed to identify these documents that defense has agreed to stipulate upon?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, you're referring to P-R1-3 up to... P-R1-25-I-1?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: No, Your Honor. We are referring to P-R1-26-20. Ah,
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: the
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: ones on
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: screen. Yes, Your Honor. For the viewing public and for the record.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, you may read the documents. All 11 of them. For the information of the counsel as well and the senator-judges while the counsel is going over it. You may proceed,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Honorable Swan.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Thank you, Your Honor. So the first letter The first document is the letter of Vice President Sara Z. Duterte to Honorable Joel Chua, Chairperson of the CGGPA, dated September 23, 2024, where the Vice President informed the committee that she will not attend the deliberations of the CGGPA and requested to terminate the inquiry. The second document is the letter of Attorney Zuleika T. Lopez, Undersecretary and Chief of Staff, OVP. to Honorable Joel R. Chua, Chairperson, CGGPA, dated October 7, 2024, where Attorney Zuleika Lopez responded to the show-cause order issued by the CGGPA to explain her failure to attend or respond to the invitations of the Committee. Number 3, the letter of Edward D. Fajarda to Honorable Joel Chua, Chairperson of the CGGPA, dated October 7, 2024, where Edward Fajarda responded to the show cause order issued by the CGGPA to explain his failure to attend or respond to the invitations of the committee. Number 4, Letter of Attorney Rosaline Sanchez, Director, Administrative and Financial Services Office, OVP to Honorable Joel Chua, Chairperson of the CGGPA dated October 7, 2024. where OVP Director Rosaline Sanchez responded to the show-cause order issued by the CGGPA to explain her failure to attend or respond to the invitations of the committee. Your Honor, we also manifest that these documents have been previously marked and the current one has been marked as P-R1-26-D as shown on the screen, Your Honor, as well as the previous documents, which were already previously marked.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: So the fifth document is the letter of Lemuel G. Ortonio, Assistant Secretary, OVP, to Honorable Joel Archua, Chairperson, CGGPA, dated October 7, 2024, where OVP ASEC Lemuel Ortonio responded to the show-cause order issued by the CGGPA to explain his failure to attend or respond. to the invitations of the committee. This was also previously marked as P-R1-26-E, sixth document. The position paper of Attorney Lopez et al. dated November 5, 2024, where Attorney Lopez, Ms. Acosta, spouses Edward and Sunshine Fajarda et al. refused to attend the CGGPA hearings and requested for termination of the inquiry by the CGGPA. This was previously marked, Your Honor, as P-R1-26-F. Seventh document, the position paper of OVP employees dated November 5, 2024, where the OVP employees refused to attend the CGGPA hearings and requested for termination of the inquiry by the CGGPA. This was previously marked as P-R1
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: 26-G. Eighth document, the letter of Gina Acosta, Sunshine Shari Fajarda, and Edward Fajarda to Honorable Joel Chua, chairperson of CGGPA, dated November 12, 2024, where Gina Acosta and spouses Edward and Sunshine Fajarda responded to the contempt order and arrest order. for their failure to attend the CGGPA hearing and this was previously marked as P-R1-26-H. Ninth, letter of Attorney Zuleika T. Lopez under Secretary and Chief of Staff, OVP, to Honorable Joel Chua, Chairperson, CGGPA, dated November 24, 2024, where Attorney Zuleika Lopez attempted to excuse her appearance in the CGGPA hearing, and this was previously marked as P-R1-26-I. Number 10, letter of Gamaliel A. Cordoba, Chairperson, Commission on Audit, with subject, Compliance with Sapina Duchesnecum, dated August 16, 2024, addressed to Honorable Sal Dico, Chairperson, Committee on Appropriations, dated August 21, 2024 where COA informed the Committee on Appropriations of the COA's compliance with the Sapina-Duches-Tecum for OVP and DepEd documents. This was marked as P-R1-26-K-1.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: And
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: last, the letter of Attorney Zuleika Lopez under Secretary and Chief of Staff, OVP. to Honorable Gamaliel Cordova, Chairperson, COA, dated August 21, 2024, where Attorney Zuleika Lopez told the COA not to comply with the subpoena by the Committee on Appropriations and refused submission of the OVP and DPED documents. This was previously marked as P-R1-26-L-1. That is it, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Comment, Attorney Linden?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, we confirm our stipulation as to the documents mentioned by the prosecution that these documents are transmitted to the archives and the archives are the custodian of these documents, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Having so stipulated, counsel, any other thing? Given that these are your four offers, I don't believe there is a need to present this witness before the court.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honor, there is still the matter of that certification that the witness issued as to the identity of these documents, the identity and faithful reproduction of these documents. If counsel will agree to stipulate, then that would be welcomed.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: May we show the certification on the screen, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: It's not so much the certification, but I guess... Without prejudice to proof being presented by counsel for the respondents that these are not faithful reproductions of the original on file, then we can presume regularity. Correct, counsel? We are amenable to that proposition, Your Honor. We can presume regularity, Honorable Suwan. Unless proof later on during cross at any stage of the trial is presented regarding the inaccuracy of these documents, we can already... Counsel is willing to stipulate. Thereby dispensing again with this witness.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Who's speaking? Yes, Honorable Son.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: If Council is willing to stipulate as to the certification, then for the record, may we have the certification marked as P-R1-26.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: It has already been marked previously. It's been
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: marked, yes.
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Just
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: for the record.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you. So, can we dispense with this witness, Honorable Son?
Rep. Lordan G. Suan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ms. Pareja, you are excused. Kindly send our regards to Cesar over there.
Marivic M. Pareja: Thank
Marivic M. Pareja: you, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: And we thank you for your time and for coming over. Thank you for your patience as well.
Marivic M. Pareja: Thank you, sir.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Call
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: your next witness, the Honorable Sua. If you're going to be the one to stand up, call your next witness, Honorable Chua.
Rep. Joel R. Chua: Your Honor, may we request Attorney Ligutan, counsel for the prosecution, to be recognized for the presentation of our next witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Ligutan is recognized for the presentation of the prosecutor's next witness. Attorney Ligutan, you may proceed when you're ready.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, we were expecting to present the witness at a bit later time.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May move for a quick recess. Two minutes, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Brief
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: recess is declared.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Clerk of Court is directed to kindly escort and situate Ms. Gina Acosta to the witness stand for her testimony.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly place the witness under oath, Atty. Bantog.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: Please raise your right hand, ma'am.
Atty. Renato N. Bantug Jr.: You, Gina F. Acosta, do swear that the evidence you shall give in the case now pending between the Philippines and Vice President Cyrus Girmayman Duterte shall be the truth, the whole truth, and nothing but the truth. So help you God.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Miss Gina, and also for the information of the Council for the Parties, we have on hand a nurse from the Senate and on call the doctors of the Senate. given that in the last appearance of Ms. Gina before the House, I believe, medyo tumaas po yung presyon ninyo. So we're just exercising some precautions with respect to this, but please try to be relaxed.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Ligutan, your witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: much, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mr. Presiding Officer, our senator-judges,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The prosecution presents the first hostile or hostile witness in this impeachment trial. The testimony of the first, we'll pronounce it as hostile, we're accustomed to hostile.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: testigo, testimonya ng kauna-unahang hostile witness sa impeachment trial na ito is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: being presented to prove Ang mga sumusunod, layo ng prosecution na ipresenta o iharap si Gina Acosta bilang isang hostile witness. Ibig sabihin hindi po siya testigo pabor sa prosecution.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pangalawa, si Ms. Acosta ay nanunungkulan ngayon bilang Vice Presidential Staff Officer VI sa Office of the Vice President. Pangatlo, Siya ay nagsilbing Special Disbursing Officer or SDO ng Office of the Vice President noong taong 2022 at 2023.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pangapat, siya rin ang nagsilbing SDO para sa Confidential Funds noong the Mayor Sara Duterte sa Davao City mula taong 2019. hanggang 2022. Panglima, siya ang naging staff member sa Davao City Administrator's Office sa pagitan ng mga taong 2016 at 2022 at ng Davao City Budget Office sa panunungkulan noon ni Mayor Sara Zimmerman Duterte. Panganim, sa last quarter o huling tatlong buwan, ng 2022, ginastos ng OVP or Office of the Vice Presidents ang halagang 125 million pesos na confidential funds sa loob lamang ng labing isang araw sa ilalim at pamamahala at pangangasiwa ng Vice Presidente ng walang liquidation ng hindi kumpleto o walang sapat na dokumento na nagpapatunay sa pagbabayad. Pangpito. Rather, pangwalo. Inatasa ng Vice Presidente ang witness na i-encash ang kabuuhang halaga na 500 million pesos or kalahating bilyon noong ikadalawampu ng Disyembre 2022, ikaanim ng Prebrero, ikadalawamputlima ng Abril, at ikalabingapat ng Hulyo 2023.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: skip number seven, sorry. Sa tatlong taon, sorry, sa tatlong three-quarters ng 2023, ginastos ng OVP. Ang halagang 375 million na confidential funds sa ilalim ng pamamahala at pangangasiwa ng vice-presidente ng walang liquidation, ng hindi, wastong liquidation rather, ng hindi kompleto o walang sapat na mga dokumento na nagpapatunay sa pagbabayan. Let's go to number nine.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ang lahat ng confidential funds na inilaan sa OVP ay nawithdraw in cold cash na nagkakahalagang kalahating bilyong piso noong December 20, 2022, February 6, April 25, at July 14, 2023. Pang-sampo, inutusan ni VP Sara na ibigay ang kabuuhang Half a billion pesos, 500 million pesos in cold cash sa security officer ng OVP na si Colonel La Chica na hindi isang accountable officer, isang paglabag sa batas sa Joint Circular 2015-01. Panglabing isa. Ang ginagawang disbursements ng confidential funds sa ilalim ng Office of the Vice President. Ang ginawang disbursements ay maraming bahid o namumutakti sa pagsuway at paglabag sa Joint Circular 2015-01. Dabing dalawa, bigo ang respondent, Vice President, na maliquidate ang kabuuhang halaga. na half a billion pesos na pera ng bayan, 500 million pesos alinsunod sa demand or kahingian ng Joint Circular Act 2015-01. Panglabing tatlo,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: dahil dito maituturing na ginastos ng Vice Presidente sa pansariling gamit at kapakinabangan
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ang half a billion pesos na pera ng bayan na confidential funds ng Office of the Vice President. Lastly, Your Honor, please, tutukuyin ng witness ang mga dokumentong may kaugnayan sa mga aligasyong nakasaan sa articles of impeachment.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That's for the offer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Comment, Atty. Bacuel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, for purposes number 2 and 3, we are willing to stipulate We note that for purpose 3, this was already part of the admissions of the parties in the pre-trial order.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: And it's contained in part 1A, item 2.8 of the pre-trial order, Your Honor. For purpose number 4 and 5, as regards the confidential funds in Davao City and the position of the witness as STO of Davao City, We would like to object on the ground of irrelevance, Your Honor, considering that for the simple reason that the confidential funds in Davao City are not part of the allegations in the articles of impeachment. So there's really no fact in issue to be proved by the testimony of the witness, Your Honor. And for all the other purposes, Your Honor, these are subject to cross-examination.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What does Attorney Ligutan say with respect to counsel's stipulation to your second and third offer? The stipulation
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: is well taken, Your Honor, please. So, therefore, it is established na si Ms. Acosta ay ngayon nanunungkulan bilang Vice Presidential Staff, Offer 6, saka nagsilbi siyang Special Dispersing Officer noong taong 2022 saka 2023. However, Your Honor, please, yung punto na walang relevance yung naging pagsisilbi as SDO para sa confidential funds mula 2019 saka 2022 saka I think union, di ba? Your Honor, please, we beg to disagree. It is very much relevant, very much relevant in today's proceedings considering, Your Honor, please, that it is her experience as the SDO of Davao City. in those inclusive years that led the Vice President to also bring her to the office of the Vice President and do and do the things they did in Davao City this time with the money of the office of the Vice President. That is very much relevant to the prosecution's case, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: May I respond, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, before the Presiding Officer makes a ruling, Counsel.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Yes, Your Honor. The rebuttal presented by the prosecution is wrong considering that there's no such allegation in the articles of impeachment, Your Honor. Moreover, Your Honor, it is clear in the ruling of the Supreme Court in Duterte v. House of Representatives that the basis of any charge must be for acts committed.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: In relation to the impeachable office and within the term of the impeachable officer, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, can I make a quick rebuttal to the last point?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: need, counsel. The presiding officer will make a ruling. The court will allow it given that it is for the purpose of establishing pattern and or behavior on the part of the witness. But to be clear, that whatever she says with respect to acts committed by her in relation to the vice president now while she was a mayor in Davao City is not part. of this impeachment trial and will not in any way add to the charges that has been filed and are pending before this court under the four articles of impeachment as previously ruled by the chair in previous requests for subpoena, for example. However, may I ask counsel further to abbreviate the proceedings? Attorney Bacal. Are you willing to stipulate that the witness is a hostile witness and therefore counsel may ask leading questions already instead of qualifying the witness as a hostile witness?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: No, Your Honor. The prosecution must first qualify the witness as hostile, Your Honor. Then
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: qualify her, Atty. Ligutan. We will. We shall. Qualify her. You may proceed when you're ready.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Madam Witness, Mayong Buntag.
Gina F. Acosta: Mayong Buntag, Saab.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, Your Honor, pwede bang magpaduulgamay sa ating grupo? Can you draw closer to the microphone?
Gina F. Acosta: Okay, okay. Salamat po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How are you, Madam Witness?
Gina F. Acosta: Okay, okay, Jutay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, okay, Jutay. Ibig sabihin, I'm a bit fine. Madam Witness, natay tubig. We have water.
Gina F. Acosta: Excuse me, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Opo.
Gina F. Acosta: Sir, pwede diniligbog na natin rin. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, ingon ng witness, sabi po ng witness, puwede bang hindi po malamig yung tubig? Um,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the, uh, OSAA is directed to kindly give her... Ma'am Gina, you prefer warm water? Hindi naman daw po malamig yan, pero baka dahil sir ko nalang lumamig.
Gina F. Acosta: Ano lang po, sir, yung kung merong maligam-gam,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: maligam-gam na lang po. Bakit bigyan na lang po ng maligam-gam?
Gina F. Acosta: Salamat po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You're welcome, ma'am. You may proceed, Atty. Ligutan. Salamat, ma'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Why are you here today, if you know?
Gina F. Acosta: Na ako diri tungod sa akong subpoena.
Gina F. Acosta: Nagipatawag ko diri sa Senado, Pitsa, August.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With your permission, Atty. Ligutan, kung papahintulutan niyo po, Ms. Gina, pwede po gamitin po ninyo para mas maunawaan ang
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: mas nakararami, Ingles o Pilipino sa pagsagot?
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, pwede po haluan ng Bisaya, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sige po, basta matranslate ni Atty. Legutan without any objection from the respondent yung ibang mga kataga o salita. Your Honor, may
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: we request an interpreter from this honorable court if this honorable court would allow? so that the defense would be able to easily understand the statements of the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: witness. We have a senator-judge who can interpret but I doubt if I can do that or will do that. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, Your Honor, I have a proposition. Ma'am Acosta, alala ko when you testified before the Committee on Good Government sa House of Representatives, ma'am, we spoke in Tagalog then sinigitan natin ng Our great Bisaya language. Pero po, para po mas mabilis, kung po pwede po, let's try as much as we could po to speak Tagalog. Kung po pwede lang ha. And then, if you really have to speak Bisaya, then of course, hindi po pinagbabawal yan. We should be proud of it. Pero kung po pwede po, Tagalog po tayo.
Gina F. Acosta: I-try po na po, sir. I will try my best po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Let's try our best po, madam.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sige, ma'am. While we're looking for a court-appointed or selected translator to get an official translation, hanggang kaya, ma'am. Pero kung hindi po, kung hindi po kayang gamitin ang ingles o wikang Pilipino, gamitin niyo po ang Bisaya o Cebuano. Subukan po naming unawain at interpret. Alright. You
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may proceed, Attorney Legudan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Salamat. Ma'am, sinabi mo, andito ka kasi nga pinasabbi na ka. Pinasabbi na ng impeachment court, di ba po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, na-mention din, na nasabi rin na ikaw ay isang special disbursing officer, hindi lang sa Davao City, pati na rin. So, office of the Vice President. Yung tanong now is, what funds?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong klaseng pondo po yung didi-disperse nyo bilang isang special disbursing officer po?
Gina F. Acosta: Confidential funds po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Confidential funds. So, na-mention mo yung confidential funds. Now, sinabi mo, ma'am, na ikaw ay andito. Kasi nga, napasabpi na ka. Ma'am, yung tanong ma'am is, ito po ba ang unang pagkakataon na kayo ay napasabpi na para tumistigo?
Gina F. Acosta: This is my second time. Pangalawang time na po ito, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And then, pag sinabi niyo pong pangalawang time, ma'am, kailan yun? Kailan yung unang pagkakataon?
Gina F. Acosta: Yung pong sa House of Representatives, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, House of Representatives. Maalala nyo yung PETSA, Ma'am? Kailan kayo nag-appear before the House of Representatives?
Gina F. Acosta: November, November 2025.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Taon po is?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong taon?
Gina F. Acosta: No, 2025.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi po 2024?
Gina F. Acosta: 2020.
Gina F. Acosta: Sandali lang sir ha. Sige,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sige. Anyways ma'am, basta sinasabi niyo po, secondary na po yung taon because it's on record naman. Pero nasabi niyo, ito po yung pangalawang pagkakataon na kayo ay naimbitahan po na tumistigo. kasi po may sabi na. Now, yung tanong ma'am is, this is preliminary question, ikaw ba ay nakatanggap na ng isang reklamong kriminal or administratiba na may pagkakaugnay sa paggamit ng confidential funds?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pleading, Your Honor. Exactly, I just said preliminary, Your Honor. Preliminary, counsel,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: witness may answer?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, Your Honor. Aha.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, sinasabi mo, Ma'am, na wala pa kayong natatanggap na reklamo. Yun po yung sagot nyo, diba? Ma'am, ipinapakita ko ngayon, Ma'am, yung isang counter-epidemic.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay? Your Honor, I move that the Prosecution Council, Attorney Jay, be allowed to confront the witness with the documents. And we'll be, that is a continuing motion because we'll be doing that for the rest of the remainder of the testimony, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Assisting counsels from both parties may approach.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Yes. Yes, Attorney Baquel.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: May we know the purpose of the questioning of the prosecution?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, I am tempted to state that but we are leading there. We are about to establish the ground for to make this witness an hostile witness. May we not be
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: preempted, Your Honor? You answered the query of counsel. You may
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: proceed. Your Honor, please. This witness, Madam Acosta, is facing a complaint together with the Vice President exactly because of their misuse of confidential funds. Your Honor. It is stated in the witnesses' counter-affidavit that the Vice President is not responsible or should not be held liable for any misuse of confidential funds. Your Honor, that interest is directly adverse to the prosecution's case before this impeachment court. The prosecution seeks to prove otherwise that this witness, that the Vice President, rather, is responsible for the illegal disbursement of confidential funds. Therefore, if on one hand, sinasabi ng testigo sa counter-affidavit niya na walang pagkakasala yung Vice President sa maling paggamit ng confidential funds, that's on one hand. On the other hand naman, sinasabi ng prosecution, Your Honor, please, na no, hindi, may ebidensya, it's so clear, na kailangan, kailangan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Managot yung Vice President for misusing public funds. Now, this is the time, Your Honor, please. Okay? If the Good Counsel will allow,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: with the presentation of a counter-affidavit by the witness stating under oath that the Vice President did not misuse confidential funds in direct conflict
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: With the prosecution's case, Your Honor, please, we now invoke Section 13, Rule 132 of the Revised Rules and Evidence, if the court may allow.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, according to Section 13, Rule 132, a witness may be considered as an unwilling or hostile if so declared by the courts upon adequate showing. Yun yung una po, Your Honor. Adverse interests.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Miss Acosta, the witness, has an adverse interest in this case as her position as shown sa counter-affidavit niya is clearly inconsistent with the position of the prosecution that called her as a witness. The prosecution presents her to prove that the respondent misappropriated confidential funds. Sa kabilang panig, sinasabi ni Ms. Acosta, yung Vice President complied sa lahat ng rules saka batas sa paggamit ng confidential funds. Sinasabi ni Ms. Acosta, hindi nag-misuse si Vice Presidente Sara Duterte ng kahit isang sentimo ng confidential funds. We now invoke the case of People v. Che Chun Ting. GR number 130-568-69 dated March 21, 2000. Supreme Court dealt with a hostile witness. Kasi nga adverse yung interest doon. Sinasabi sa kaso ngayon, having an adverse interest meant, eto, that the position or interest was adverse to what the party called or wanted to establish or prove. yun po yung bataya ng Supreme Court. Kung yung posisyon ng isang witness ay salungat sa posisyon ng partidong nagpapatawag sa kanya, sa kaso ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: iyan, sabi ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Supreme Court, established na po yung requirement ng adverse interests sa ilalim ng rules of courts.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, the respondent respectfully submits that the adverse interest must be shown by the prosecution through an examination of the witness and not through a mere motion or manifestation, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: He just did, counsel, by showing the position taken by the witness in her counter-affidavit.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Additionally, Your Honor, the defense also submits that the mere fact of dependency of the criminal case This not satisfy the requirement of adverse interest under the rules of evidence, considering that it apparently constitutes to a mere expectation that the witness will testify unfavorably to the prosecution, which is not within the ambit of the rules. Considering that the declaration of a witness as hostile presupposes that the prosecution would face difficulty in obtaining answers from the witness on account of such adverse interests, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Allow the presiding officer. Ms. Gina? Saan po kayo nagtatrabaho ngayon sa Office of the Vice President? Tama po?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sino po ang boss niyo sa Office of the Vice President?
Gina F. Acosta: Si Vice President Sara Duterte.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Permanente po ba kayo doon o coterminous?
Gina F. Acosta: Coterminous po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So pag wala na si VP Sara doon sa OBP, wala na rin po kayo?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So pag na-impeach si VP Sara o matanggal siya, wala na rin po kayong trabaho doon?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala na po akong trabaho sa OVP.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sa OVP, syempre. Maalis kayo sa OVP. Tama po?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: In addition to the ground raised by Attorney Ligutan, that witness has taken a position by virtue of her counter-affidavit filed before the Office of the Ombudsman. The court hereby declares the witness to be a hostile witness under and in accordance with Rule 132, Section 13. However, for the information of the senator-judges and the public and councils as well, this only gives Attorney Ligutan the right to ask leading questions, still not allowed to ask misleading questions. As I know, Attorney Ligutan is well aware of the distinction.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. To abbreviate the proceedings, the witness is so declared and Attorney Ligutan may ask leading questions of this witness. It's ordered.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Maraming salamat. Madam Witness, kayo po, ma'am, ay isang hostile witness na. So, ma'am, I can now ask you questions. Sorry for a brief beside. Pero, ma'am, wala tanag-away, ha? We are not enemies. Okay? Andito po tayo sa isang bagay lang. Ano yung totoo? kung sa'y tinuod, kung sa'y kamaturan. Let's proceed. Madam Witness, you already mentioned, in fact established, na bago ka naging SDO para sa Office of the Vice President, ikaw rin ang SDO na nag-a-handle ng confidential funds po para sa Davao City. Alala mo po ba yan? Your Honor. That's preliminary, preliminary, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Baquel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: are at issue in this case, Your Honor. Can I respond
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: to
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: that,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The Chair already made a ruling in regard to that, Attorney Baquel. We will allow it to establish pattern and or behavior but not to add to the articles of impeachment against the Vice President. That is quite clear. Not only to counsels, but also to the senator-judges and for the public as well. But the Chair would like to note, if you would like to make one, a continuing objection insofar as this line of questioning is concerned. Yes, Your Honor. Continuing objection of counsel to this line of questioning is hereby noted. Thank you so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: much. We are also, we
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: will be continually invoking isang rule sa rules a procedure Rule 130, Section 35. Exactly. I think that's what the honorable presiding officer had in mind. Rule 130, Section 5. Allowing presentation of evidence on previous acts to prove specific intent, knowledge, identity, plan, system, scheme, habit, custom, usage, or the like.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: maaintindihan ng ating mga kababayan, pattern. May pattern.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May proceed, Your Honor? You may proceed, counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you. So therefore, madam, yung paghahandle po ng confidential funds hindi na bago sa inyo. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Ano po, Your Honor? Pamilya lang po ako sa pagiging SDO, Special Disbursement Officer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright, now. And ma'am, familiar din po kayo sa mga dokumento or reports na kailangang ihanda bago po magamit
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: isang opisina gaya ng Office of the Vice President ng Confidential Funds. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor. Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much, ma'am. In fact, madam,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You are familiar with Joint Circular 2015-01. In particular, nakasaad dyan, paragraph 4.2. May we be allowed, Your Honor, please, to... Ayan. Ma'am, nakasulat po sa paragraph 4.2 ng Joint Circular 2015-01 na lahat ng allocations ng confidential funds Dapat supported by yung unang dokumento, ma'am, nakasulat dyan, physical and financial plan. Familiar po kayo sa provision na ito, ma'am, di ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ma'am. Salamat po. Now, according sa provision na ito, ang pagdi-disperse, okay, ang paggagamit, Ma'am, what's Visaya for disbursement? Kung alam niyo po. Ano ba yung Visaya? What term do we use? Cebuano-Visaya for disbursement?
Gina F. Acosta: Ang pag-release.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pag-release. Okay. Kailangan base yan sa physical and financial plan. Okay. Therefore, hindi po pwede na may marirelease na confidential funds kung walang tinatawag na PFP. No? physical and financial plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tama po, ma'am. Di po ba, ma'am, kinukumpirma mo na para sa ikaapat at huling quarter ng 2022 para mairelease yung 125 million pesos na confidential funds, sinasabi niyo, nag-comply naman yung Office of the Vice President sa kinakailangang physical and financial plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tama po ba? Now, in fact, ma'am, pumerma ka at nagsumiti kayo ng isang physical and financial plan na yung petsa is December 13, 2022. Tama po ba, ma'am?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi ko maalala exactly ang number, Your Honor, pero nag-himot niyo physical financial plan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Dagnaghimo, Your Honor, means gumawa sila ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: physical and
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: financial plan. Thank you so much. Now, so para po maalala natin, ma'am, ipapakita natin ngayon yung isang physical and financial plan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Mark as P-I-14-1 for the prosecution. Show the document on the screen.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: and to the witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, yung physical and financial plan, ipinirmahan po ni Rosalyn Sanchez tsaka ni Sara Z. Duterte. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, maalala mo now yung dokumentong ito. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. And
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: then, base sa dokumentong ito, ma'am, sinasabi dyan, ikaw yung tinatawag natin na Project Accountable Officer. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In fact, ma'am, you will also confirm na pinirmahan niyo po yung PFP as the Project Accountable Officer. Nakasulat dyan, ma'am. Diba, ma'am, nakasulat dyan? Prepared by. Ibig sabihin, kayo po, ma'am, yung nag-prepare.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ng PFP. Based on document. Based on document.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor, pero during paghimuan ni Your Honor, kasama ko po ang aming security officer, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: By paghimuan, it means while we were making this, I was with the our security officer. Ma'am, tama po yung interpretation ko, di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Kasama ko po ang aming security officer, Your Honor, kasi Sa kanya po ako nakihingi ng mga inputs or guidelines in preparation for the fiscal financial plan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Maraming salamat for that. But we will go into that, ma'am. We will go into that. Taabot po tayo sa punto niyan. Okay po, ma'am? Now, ma'am, bilang po project accountable officer, ikaw nakasulat dyan, ikaw yung nagprepara ng plano, ikaw din. being the officer, accountable officer. Yung naglista ng mga confidential funds. Ma'am, yung paglista, ma'am, ha? Yung tanong ko, ha? Paglista ng confidential funds, programs, and activities na nasusulat sa physical and financial plan. Di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Pwede usabon, Your Honor, ang question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ako usabon, ma'am, no? Bilang project accountable officer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: The one who prepared the plan, ikaw din yung naglista. Yung naglista ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tulad.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa plano, sa plan, ano yung mga programa at activities? Yung paglilista po. Kayo po yun, di ba? As the project accountable officer, the one who prepared the plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po with the...
Gina F. Acosta: tulong po ng security officer. Yes, ma
Gina F. Acosta: 'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We'll go into that. Ma'am, let's continue. Now, makikita natin sa plano, ma'am, na inlistan nyo under the column programs with an S, activities with an S, projects with an S,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: PAP. Ma'am, ano yung nakasulat dyan? Ano yung programa sa mga programs?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: activities, projects. Anong programa yung sinulat niyo dyan? Good governance program.
Gina F. Acosta: Sorry, Your Honor. Hadikai. Dilikayo ko.
Gina F. Acosta: Dilikayo ko kabasa, Your Honor, kay Gagmay Kayo ang letra. The
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: witness
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: said hindi niya kayang basahin dahil maliit yung mga letra.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, you can peruse the document even without. Okay? Pwede ba mas? Ayan, ma'am, di ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Good governance program.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Ligutan, if you're approaching the witness, kindly bring the mic para hindi mahirapan yung ating gumagawa ng TSN.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Now, ma'am, okay
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: na po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Okay po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, now, yung tanong is, ano ba
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: itong
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: good governance program na ito? What is this all about?
Gina F. Acosta: Ito po yung mga programa ng opisina ng Office of the Vice President na nakalista na po sa buong taon. Halimbawa po, yung libring sakay, yung plant at risk millionaires, or million, kalimutan ko sir, libring sakay, yung financial, medical, Medical assistance, Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor. Okay. So, ma'am, yun yung mga sinasabi mong mga programa under this program. Yun yung sinasabi mo, di ba? Ma'am, sino po yung nag-conceptualize? Sino pong bumuo o nag-isip ng programang ito?
Gina F. Acosta: Ang opisina po ng Office of the Vice President, Your Honor, with coordination po sa aming security officer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now. Kailan po nabuo ang planong ito?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa security officer naman, yung nag-conceptualize, di po ba,
Gina F. Acosta: ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: mga planong ito?
Gina F. Acosta: Repeat, Your Honor, sa question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sino yung kailan na conceptualize? Ito yung tanong. Kailan nabuo or napag-isipan or na-conceptualize itong good governance program? Kailan?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa pag... Sa pag ano na, Your Honor, pag kimo na o pag-request na ni Ma'am VP ng confidential funds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: When the Vice President requested for confidential funds. Ma'am, may mga pag-aaral ba o pagsasaliksik na ginawa ang inyong opisina to come up with the program?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala akong personal knowledge, Anna, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May proseso ba o kriteriya na ginamit to select of all programs, good governance programs? Wala po.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala akong kabalo, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: By wala'y kabalo, it means wala po akong personal knowledge. Wala po akong alam.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We're fine here, okay?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Let's continue, Your Honor. You may continue, counsel, but the public is reminded to kindly put their phones in silent mode.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sinabi niyo, ma'am, na wala po kayong alam, wala kayong personal knowledge, kasi po, hindi naman po ikaw yung nag-identify ng mga programa. Tsaka mga activities na nakasulat sa 2022 Physical and Financial Plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In fact, ma'am, you will admit, confirm, na noong November 25, 2024, yung pagdinig ng Committee on Good Governments and Accountability, you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: merely ask a security officer Colonel La Chica. What to state in the physical and financial plan as confidential activities in relation sa paggamit ng Office of the Vice President ng Confidential Funds. To aid your memory, Your Honor, please, we are showing on the screen, on the screen, a portion of the transcript of the Committee on Good Government and Accountability hearing. November 25, 2024 where sinasabi ng witness that all information that will be reflected in the physical and financial plan of the Office of the Vice President which she prepared galing lang sa isang security officer si Colonel Achica.
Gina F. Acosta: Siya po ang nagbigay sa akin ng inputs, Your Honor, or mga guidelines, Your Honor, kung ano po ang mga activities in relation po sa pagkandak po ng confidential operations or activities.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Salamat, ma'am. Ma'am, who is this Colonel La Chica?
Gina F. Acosta: Si
Gina F. Acosta: Colonel La Chica po ay siya po ang commanding officer ng aming BPSPG, at siya din ang aming security officer ng Office of the Vice President.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Si Colonel La Chica, yung full name niya po ay si Colonel Raymond Dante La Chica. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Muna yung full name, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yun yung full name niya. Now, thank you so much. Nag-agsalamat, ma'am. Now, hindi po ba na-aside po na si La Chica? Colonel La Chica yung magsasabi sa iyo ano yung isusula sa plan, hindi po ba na the same? Colonel La Chica, yung nagbibigay sa iyo ng mga listahan ng object of expenditures where the confidential funds will be used. Ma'am, before you answer that, to remind you, eto naman, page 126 po ng transcript of the C. GGPA hearing dated November 25, 2024.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nakasaad dyan, inamin niyo, under oath ma'am, na iyong nagbibigay sa iyo ng listahan ng object of expenditures, paano gagamitin yung confidential funds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ikaw po yung nagprepara, pero si Col. La Chica yung nagsasabi sa iyo sa mga listahan ng paggagamitan ng confidential funds. Based on that transcript. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Sorry, Your Honor, nalibog ko sa imahang question. Taas man kaayo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We have to clarify. By nalibog, ibig sabihin, confused. Na-confused po. Now, ma'am, base po sa November 25, 2024 hearing, inamin niyo po na si Colonel La Chica yung nagbibigay sa iyo ng listahan ng Object of Expenditures for Confidential Funds. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Object of Expenditures. Yes, Your Honor. Yes, Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor. Nag
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: -agsalamat, ma'am. Ma'am, eto na yung tanong, ma'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Isn't it po na yung paggagawa, pagpre-prepara ng plano, tsaka yung pagdidetali, pagdidetali ng Objects of
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: expenditures,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: hindi po ba trabaho niyo yun? Bilang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: special
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: disbursing officer being the project accountable officer as indicated in the plan prepared by. Hindi po ba dapat kayo yun?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel for the respondent. We respectfully
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: object, Your Honor. on the ground of being compound and argumentative, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection is overruled. Witness may answer.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pakisagot po yung tanong, Ma 'am
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Gina.
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, pwede po usbon ang iyang pangutana. Taas mang good, Your Honor. Yes, Ma
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 'am. I will, Ma'am. Para kay Gina Acosta, I will do that. Ma'am.
Gina F. Acosta: Salamat.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay now, hindi po ba na yung pagdadraft ng physical and financial plan, trabaho niyo bilang project accountable officer as indicated by the note prepared by in the plan. Di ba trabaho niyo dapat yan?
Gina F. Acosta: Trabaho ko po yan with the inputs or guidelines sa aming security officer, Your Honor. Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ma'am. Ma'am, hindi po ba? na yung paglilista ng expenditures, ma'am, sa planong iyan, as indicated by the note, prepared by you being the project accountable officer, hindi po ba trabaho niyo rin po yan?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Ask and answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wala, iba yun. Yung kanina was drafting, now is detailing of the list of expenses.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly address the court, counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer.
Gina F. Acosta: Ano po yun, sir?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, kanina sinabi mo yung pag-prepare para trabaho niyo with inputs ni Colonel Chica. Yung tanong nao is, yung paglilista, pagdidetalye ng expenditures. Opo, di ba trabaho niyo rin po yan as SDO slash Project Accountable Officer as indicated by the note, prepared by.
Gina F. Acosta: Ang pagsulat po, ako, pero ang... Ang mga expenses po kung unsa ang gamiton kay Sir, kay security officer po kasi siya po ang mag-implement ng various confidential operation activities. Kaya siya po ang eksperto dito sa ground, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So therefore, ma'am, kayo po yung taga-sulat sa lahat ng gustong ispasulat ni Colonel Achica. Tama po ba?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Misleading, Your Honor. Misleading, counsel. The witness did not say that. She said she was getting inputs from Colonel La Chica. Your Honor, that's a follow-up question, Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: please. That's a
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: follow-up question. So I'm confirming with her that it was Colonel La Chica who told her what to write, what to input. That's the question, Your Honor, please. On the basis of her previous answer that it was with the inputs of Colonel La Chica. So that's a question by itself, Your Honor, please. A follow-up question.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina, kayo po ang nagta-type dito sa form na to. Pag sinabing prepared by you, kayo po yung nag-type, nag-sulat.
Gina F. Acosta: Ako po ang nag-sulat, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pero kinukuha niyo po yung sinusulat ninyo mula kay Colonel Lachica. Kumukuha po kayo ng input sa kanya kung anong ita-type o isusulat niyo dyan.
Gina F. Acosta: After we discuss, po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pagkatapos niyo mag-usap ni Colonel Lachica.
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ibig sabihin po ba nun, pwede niyong sabihin kay Colonel Lachica, maliyag. Hindi pwede yan.
Gina F. Acosta: O
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: sinusunod niyo lang po lahat ng sinasabi niya?
Gina F. Acosta: Mangutana, nangutana ako sa iya, Your Honor, kung unsan na, Your Honor, ngano ka na ang gastuhon, Your Honor, asa na, paunsan na siya maka, maka, paunsan na siya na related sa confidential, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So tinatanong niyo lang po siya, ano yan, para saan yan, pasok ba yan sa confidential, paano hindi, at pag sumagot siya, isusunod niyo po yan.
Gina F. Acosta: Kung ma-satisfy ko po sa iyong i-explain sa ko ay Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pag nakontento kayo sa paliwanag niya, ilalagay niyo po.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Okay. Tony Ligudan,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: your witness. Thank you so much. Now, going back, Madam Witness, going to the physical and financial plan for the so-called Good Governance Program, you will confirm you allocated 125 million pesos. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In facts, ma'am, as can be seen, show the plan again.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: did not list specific activities under the good governance program. Ulitin ko, wala po kayong inilista ng mga specific particular activities under the good governance program. Wala po kayong nakalistang specific activities.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Original document rule, Your Honor. Can
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I explain? Can I rebut that? Witness may... What's your comment, Attorney Legutan? Your Honor, I would not... I don't want to put the defense on the spot. Your Honor, please. That is, with all respect, a wrong invocation of the original document rule. The original document rule simply states na hindi po pwede...
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi po puwedeng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: magpresenta ng ebidensya na secondary kung hindi ipipresenta yung original. Pero Your Honor, the fact na yung original ay nasa harap na sa isang witness, I don't see anywhere in the rules that will prohibit counsel from propounding questions. on the basis of that document.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: me...
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Besides counsel, Atty. Bachel, the counsel is not trying to change the contents of the document. He's merely asking the witness to explain the contents of the document. Ms. Acosta, you may answer, ma'am. Ang nilagay niyo lamang po, good governance... Ano
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: po yan? Program po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Programs at wala po kayo nilagay na detalye ng mga programang yan.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala po akong nilagay na detail, Your Honor, kasi sa GC po, Your Honor, wala naman po nakabutang dito na i-itemize, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, let's go to paragraph 6.1 ng Joint Circular 2015.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, show it please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Di po ba sa 6.1 sinasabi dyan? Cash advances shall be used for specific legal purpose.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: At saka 5.2.2, nakasulat dyan, agencies shall report the specific detail of the corresponding expenditures. In two instances po, nakasulat sa joint circular yung term na specific. And you will stand by your answer. Argumentative, Your Honor. Wait, wait,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: wait.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm just confirming. I'm just confirming. Despite these two provisions, you are of the opinion, Madam, na
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: walang requirement na dapat specific. Argumentative,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Objection is overruled. Witness will answer, please.
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, sa mga dokumento po nga i-attach dito sa confidential funds liquidation, dagahan po ang document, Your Honor, na i-submit ni mo nga na ay documents dito na kailangan i-itemize ni mo, Your Honor. In
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the report. Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor. sa isa sa
Gina F. Acosta: mga dokumento na i-attach nimo dito, i-liquidate nimo sa confidential funds, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. Let me state that for the record. Correct me if I'm wrong, Ma'am Gina.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung binabanggit po niyong pag-comply, walang nakalagay specifically sa joint circular, na dapat specific yun, dun sa, what's that, counsel? physical and financial plan po. Pero sa dokumentong sinasubmit, nandoon na
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: yung mga detalye, ma'am Gina.
Gina F. Acosta: Inanak, Your Honor.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: There is only, this is another question now. There is only a blanket program, general program, good governance program in the plan and the plan did not mention any surveillance operations by specific number, location or cost. Do you want me to repeat the question or you can answer now?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Askin answered and original document rule, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Not yet answered, counsel. And again, same ruling as your point on the original document rule. Ma
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 'am, yung tanong is, wala pong specific mention ng specific number, location, or cost ng mga sinasabi niyong surveillance operations. Wala doon sa plano, di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: pwede mangutana, Your Honor, unsan ang documento, Your Honor. Katong
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: plano po, yung plano po, physical and financial plan. Nakasulat dyan, good governance program. Anyways, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: At this juncture, I will agree with counsel for the respondent. Asked and answered, counsel. That's her answer. Thank you so much. Now, aside
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: from walang surveillance operations by number, location, or cost, wala ding specific targets nakasulat sa plano. for each of the program activities. Tama po ba? Walang specific targets this time.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: By
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: all
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: means po.
Gina F. Acosta: For 2022, Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: saan
Gina F. Acosta: mo ang physical financial plan, Your Honor, na ikulong dito nga physical target, Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, mayroon. Ma'am, yung tanong is, nakasulat lang dyan is, ma'am o, number, period, of identified areas of surveillance conducted and monitored, and then yung pangalawa, letter B, yung ano lang, yung simbolo ng percentage, no? Percentage of activities implemented without specifying, una po, this is the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: first question, ano yung actual number? Wala po, di po ba? Yes po?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala pa, Your Honor, kaya wala pa manay tabo. Plano pa manay, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So wala pa kasi plano pa lang and then you asked for 125 million pesos. Kahit wala pang activities, plano pa lang. Tama po ba? Misleading, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That's a
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: follow-up question, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection is sustained.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ask based on the document, counsel.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You're referring to the physical target only. Yes, sir. Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sir. Now, nakalagay ba dyan yung actual number?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no? May numero ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala pa, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. May naka-indicate ba na percentage, actual percentage under the category percentage of activities implemented? Wala po ba? Meron ba? Wala.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala pa, Your Honor. Pero gihimon na, Your Honor, kay naanay approval. Kung asa minakabalo, kung pila ang kwarta, Your Honor, kay naanay saru.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Now, okay. Ma'am. Kindly translate that for the record. Who can translate that, please?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It's indicated because there is already a saru. if the defense will stipulate on that interpretation.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: You may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: have
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: your own.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The translation we're getting is it's not The number and percentage is not there. Yung percentage po at yung bilang, wala po doon. Dahil kaka-release pa lang ng SARO. Tama po ma'am?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. As best as we could, counsel. Please proceed.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, the 2022 physical and financial plan allocated, ma'am, nag-allocate po ng 125 billion pesos kahit walang breakdown ng amount for for each specific activity. Tama po ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: As
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you answered, Your Honor. There's another angle as to the amount relative to the activity as to the budget that the Office of the Vice President is asking. It's the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: same point, Your Honor. Same point, Counsel. Move on. We get what you have established.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Thank you so much. Now, therefore, Madam Witness, yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Office of the Vice President can just include, pupwedeng,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: i
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: -include, i-sama ng Office of the Vice President sa liquidation reports ng kahit anong activity so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: long as ililabel siya na parte ng broad good governance program. Do you want me to repeat the question or you can answer now?
Gina F. Acosta: I will.
Gina F. Acosta: Clarify, Your Honor. Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, if the court may allow, I will repeat the question. Therefore, madam, kasi nga walang breakdown, in draft sa paggawa niyo ng liquidation report,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: pupwede niyong isama doon sa liquidation report ng kahit anong aktibidad so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: long as sasabihin niyo
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: partyan ng good governance program. Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the basis?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection, counsel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Misleading and speculative, Your Honor. It's
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: not counsel. In fact, I think that's one of the questions some of the senator-judges will ask.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 'am,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: naintindihan
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: niyo po yung tanong? Ma'am Gina, naintindihan niyo po yung tanong?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Good governance, good governance, what's that
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel? Programs? Good governance program po. Good governance program, ang tanong po niya. So, ano man yung sabihin nila, basta sabihin good governance program, pasok na po yan doon? Sa report po, sa report. Sa report lang po.
Gina F. Acosta: Sa report na liquidation po. Your Honor, kung pag-ibon ako o liquidation report, nagbasi po ako sa fund utilization report na gihatag sa ako saan mo ang security officer, Your Honor,
Gina F. Acosta: na
Gina F. Acosta: makita dito kung asan na gasto ang kwarta unsa nga mga expenses o pila, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ang pinagbabasihan niyo po yung liquidation report noong security officer na si Colonel Lachica, tama po?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Out of curiosity, May tinanggihan ba kayong liquidation report na sinabmit ni Cornella Chica o lahat po nang binigay niya sayo ay tinanggap mo na parte ng Good Governance Program?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Meron po ba kayong tinanggihan na liquidation na sinabmit si Cornella Chica sa 125 million sa last quarter ng 2022 o lahat po nang sinumitin niya na liquidation, tinanggap niyo at sa pananaw niyo ay kasama ng Good Governance Program?
Gina F. Acosta: Ang lahat ng mga Lahat ng mga reports na giwihatag niya sa koa, Your Honor, akong gidawat, Your Honor, kay siyaman ang nakabalo unsaon pag-implementar sa mga confidential activities, kay siya ang eksperto, Your Honor, dito sa ground,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Lahat po nang binigay niya sa inyo, tinanggap niyo, at kinonsideran ninyo na parte ng good governance program dahil saan naman niyo nakakaalam at intindi, dahil saan naman niyo nasa ground.
Gina F. Acosta: Inanay, Your Honor. Yes, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor. Let me continue on that point, counsel, with your permission and indulgence. So yung tree planting, good governance program po yun.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: tree planting, binanggit niyo po kanina, tree planting, good governance program po yun. Kasama po yun doon sa pag-liquidate?
Gina F. Acosta: Ang ibig sabihin, Your Honor, sa pag-gihing mo ang tree planting, Your Honor, na ay gihing mo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ang sinatanong ko po, ma'am, yung activity
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: na
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: tree planting Barte po yun ng good governance sa pagkakaunawa ninyo na program. Yes or no, ma'am?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor, pero usada gihim mo, Your Honor, ang security officer, Your Honor, na gihim mong surveillance, monitoring, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Nabasa ko po yun. Pati yung libring sakay, part ng good governance.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: May surveillance din po doon. Nakita ko po sa liquidation report.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: counsel, proceed. Thank you so much. Yun yung liquidation report.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the point is, punta naman tayo sa accomplishment report. Kasi nga, iba yun, diba? Now, same line of question, but this time, different document.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You can just include. Pupwede nyong isulat sa accomplishment report.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kahit anong na lang activity, kahit anong activity in the accomplishment report this time, not liquidation reports, so long as ililabel niyo lang under yan ng good governance program. You want me to repeat the question, ma'am, or you can answer now?
Gina F. Acosta: Accomplishment
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: report this time. Yung kanina po, nag-guess nyo na, liquidation report. Ngayon ngayon yung tanong is sa accomplishment report naman, pareho lang. Kahit anong activity, isasama sa accomplishment report so long as isusulat under good governance program. Tama po ba?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, can you confront the witness with the accomplishment report? Assisting counsel, can you forward the accomplishment report?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Para maunawaan ang
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: testigo na ibang dokumento na ang pinag-uusapan natin, kanina yung physical and financial plan, ngayon naman yung accomplishment report.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pakitingnan po at pag-aralan yung dokumento, Ma'am Gina, para alam niyo po na yan ang tinutukoy ni Atty. Ligutan sa mga katanungan po niya sa inyo.
Gina F. Acosta: Excuse me, Your Honor.
Gina F. Acosta: Kajuhamin Agihimo o Accomplishment Report, Your Honor, for 2022.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: ma
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 'am.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kung dalawang beses kayo, dalawang beses po kayo gumawa ng Accomplishment Report, Ma'am Gina?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Alin po yan? Yung nauna o yung sumunod?
Gina F. Acosta: Ang kaninggatag sakwa, Your Honor, mauni ang unang Agihimo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung unang Accomplishment Report. Do you have
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: a copy of the second report? We can leave with one report.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For this
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: point, Your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Honor, please. I'll ask the direct question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Madam
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness, you are
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: confirming that there are activities in your report, in the liquidation, in the Accomplishment Report that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you have
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: read,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: and financial plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, pagimol na po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, this time po, I hope you don't mind po. The question is simple. So, puwede kang tanungin ng abogado ng kabila. Pero, pag-isagot lang po muna.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: The witness is answering, Your Honor. Let the witness answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Allow the witness to answer,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May mga aktibidades, activities, programa, kalihukan. in Visaya. Reflected in the reports, accomplishment reports, na hindi naman mababasa, makikita, nailista sa physical and financial plan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Libog. Nalito ako, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Anyways, Your Honor. Ma'am, sa accomplishment report, yes, Senator-Judge Zubiri, would you like to offer your services?
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Yes, actually, not the services to interpret, but it's possible that Attorney Ligutan could ask the question in Bisaya, so that Mama Costa can understand.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: And then, anyway, it can be objected to by the defense because I know there are three or four of you, Bisaya, Taga Cebu, Tulu, Tulumo Ria, Nakasabot. So you can always object if the translation of Attorney Ligutan is wrong. is different. It's simple Bisaya naman.
Sen. Juan Miguel “Migz” F. Zubiri: Makasabot man ta, pero ang mga Tinagalog din hindi kasabot. But you know, it's very simple. So maybe that way we don't have to keep stopping. Attorney Ligutan can ask the question first in Tagalog and then translate to simple Bisaya. Makatubag ni si ma'am. She can answer. And then... Attorney Ligutan can offer the answer also in Tagalog. If it is not like, of course, approved by the defense, the defense can give a clarification of what the answer of the lady witness has.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The point of the Senator-Judge is well taken. Let's try to do that, counsels, with your permission.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Bakel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Yes, Your Honor. May we respectfully suggest for a Court-appointed interpreter, considering that hindi po kasi ako bisaya, so actually nahihirapan po ako to understand the witness, understand Attorney Ligutan, and understand my colleagues who are likewise.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: If you may, if you will please. We already have an interpreter, actually two of them here, that will course it through the chair if there is a need to do so. Some of the words are understandable.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Anyway, I'm kindly proceed slowly, Attorney Ligutan. But on this issue and this question, Ms. Acosta, ang tanong po sa inyo, may mga nilagay po kayong accomplishment report sa accomplishment report na wala dun sa physical and financial plan. Na sinabi niyo lamang o tinisip niyo lang kasama yan sa good governance program.
Gina F. Acosta: Accomplishment report, Your Honor, is yung mga expenses na allowable po sa confidential funds.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Opo, pero wala nga po yan, hindi yan nilagay doon sa physical and financial plan. Nakalagay lang po sa accomplishment report.
Gina F. Acosta: Sa
Gina F. Acosta: accomplishment report, Your Honor, actual.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kaya nga, doon nga lang po nakasulat. Sa physical and financial plan, wala po doon.
Gina F. Acosta: Generic po ang sa physical and financial plan, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ligutan,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: continue.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's a
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: cue to the next question.
Gina F. Acosta: And
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: because the program indicated in the plan is broad and general, generic sabi niyo, so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: much discretion is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: given to the Office of the Vice President on how to utilize confidential funds. Translate into Tagalog, unfortunately I'll be needing What's Tagalog for this question po?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kasi
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: nga broad general yung program nakasulat sa PFP.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Maski ano na lang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: kahit
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: anong gustong gawin magagawa ng Office of the Vice President sa paggamit
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Confidential funds. You want to state in Visaya po?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kay tungod.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: General. Generic. Ang programang nakasulat sa plano.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Bisag unsa.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So much discretion. Ma'am, I think you understand discretion, di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Um, authority?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Dako ang pagbuot sa office of the Vice President kung unsaon nila paggamit. sa confidential funds. Tama po ba? Objection,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the objection, counsel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Speculative and argumentative, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: It's not argumentative, counsel. Neither is it speculative. Objection overruled. Ma'am Gina, dahil po kayo nagsabi generic yung good governance program, malaking laya ang nabigay sa inyo. para magsulat ng kung anumang mga programa na papasok doon sa generic na good governance program.
Gina F. Acosta: Duly, Your Honor, kaya
Gina F. Acosta: nagbasi
Gina F. Acosta: ako sa Joint Circular 2015.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So ang sagot ay hindi. Hindi ganun kalaki ang kalayaang meron sila dahil binasin niya yung kanyang accomplishment report sa JC2015-1. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Rigutan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, showing you again, Madam Witness, the 2022 physical and financial plan. After you prepared the plan, it was noted by a certain Rosaline Sanchez. Is that
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: correct?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor. The document please. And thereafter,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You presented the plan kay Inday Sara, Vice President Sara,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: for her approval. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Di
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: pakitaan
Gina F. Acosta: ako sa iyo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In this case, did she provide any feedback on the stated generic, coming from your own mouth, good governance program?
Gina F. Acosta: What is it,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm sure you know feedback.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Saan po pumirma si Sara Zimmerman Duterte? Sa parte ng plano, saan jan?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa approve.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Approved by, showing on screen, approved by Sara Z. Duterte, Vice President, Agency Head, Department Secretary, LCE.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With the indulgence of Attorney Ligutan, what is the pleasure of Senator-Judge Erwin Tulfo?
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Mr. President, I have here the transcript of the hearing in Congress.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Hindi ko po maintindihan bakit parang dito hirap na hirap po siya magtagalog when in fact sa Congress po noong November, itagalog naman po ang sagot niya. Ang tanong po sa kanya ni Congressman Luistro, payment of incentive, 11 po. Would you know whether this amounts would total 120 exactly? Yes, ma'am. Gitotal ko po iyan, ma'am. 120
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: million po.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: It's all... Puro Tagalog, Mr. President. What is this? I mean, mabuti po sana pati yung discretionary. And she's a government official. She doesn't know what discretionary means is. I mean, what it means. Dito po, sumasagot naman po siya. English, Tagalog. Yes po. Are you aware of my authority, Special Dispersing Officer? Kasi po wala akong alam kung paano po i-implement ang mga confidential. Mr. President, tama na po itong paluloko sa atin. Please, Mr. President, compel this witness to talk in Tagalog. Kahit po yung mga Bisaya po nakaintindi ng Tagalog, nakakasalita ng Tagalog, ano tayo sa ibang bansa? Ano tayo? Mga Japon? Mga Chinese? I know, Ms. Witness, you can understand. You can understand Tagalog. You can speak Tagalog. Dahil nandito po ito. Ilang pahina po ito.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: Tagalog po yung sagot po ninyo. English po, sumasagot kayo. Tinatanong kayo ng English, sumasagot po kayo. Bakit ngayon parang hirap na hirap? Kailangang i-translate sa Tagalog, sa Bisaya. Sagot, Tagalog, Bisaya, Tagalog, Bisaya. E abutin mo tayo ng
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: isang taon dito, Mr. President. Ito po, yo.
Sen. Erwin Tulfo: That's all, Mr. President.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank you, Senator-Judge Erwin Tulfo. Point well taken. Attorney Ligutan, to abbreviate the proceedings, kindly choose one language, English or Filipino, in asking the question. You don't have to translate each time unless the witness requests you to do so.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Preferably use Filipino, Attorney Ligutan, as I'm sure you're well versed with it as well.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes. Since
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you said, inapprobahan po ng vice president yung plano kasama sa inapprobahan ng vice president yung generic good governance program.
Gina F. Acosta: I
Gina F. Acosta: approve, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. In fact, ma'am, yun din po yung naging tugon niyo sa same line of questioning. noong November 25, 2024. As shown by that portion of that transcript, you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: confirm that it was may approval po ng head of agency at saka yung head of agency is the respondent in this case, Sara Zimmerman Duterte, Vice President. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Let's proceed po sa susunod na punto. Let's go to the physical and financial plan naman. This time, para naman sa 2023.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: From good governance program, ma'am, this time, Atty. J,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: it can be seen sa plano, this time, hindi na good governance program, kundi nakasunod dyan, socio-economic program.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Delivery. With the indulgence of counsel, can the tech please zoom in? Yes, kindly zoom in.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Proceed, Your Honor. Ms. Gina will please answer, kindly confirm, ang nakasulat na po sa 2023 ay yung socio-economic program delivery.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi na po good governance program.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Proceed, Your Honor.
Gina F. Acosta: But,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: but, sa 2023 physical and financial plan
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: expected outcome naman nananatili. 2022 na expected outcome. Nakasulat, safe implementation of OVP initiatives and confidence building for 2022. Same expected outcome, safe implementation of OVP initiatives and confidence building. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor. Ma
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 'am, puwedeng mas malapit pa sa mikropono para po marinig. Again, may tubig diyan, ma'am, ha? If you want to drink water now. Therefore, masasabi natin, base sa dokumento, ma'am, yung 2023 physical and financial plan, kopya lang.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kopya lang ng number one, physical target, Galing sa 2022. Tama po ba?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. The document would speak for itself because the prosecution is asking the witness what is already based on the document as the question is framed, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer. I'm just not so sure if she understands the word copy. So, Ma'am Gina, pareho lang po ang nilalaman ng physical and financial plan.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor. Now
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: proceed. Same with budget for each quarter.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Fourth quarter ng 2023, ma'am. Kopyang kopya yung amount. 125 million pesos. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama, Your Honor, kay Ma'am Manda ang nakabutang saga, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Proceed, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung may
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: tama daw dahil yung daw ang nakalagay is saga.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Both the 2020 2022 physical and financial plan and the 2023 version provided for broad program under po sa programs, activities, and projects sa 2022 good governance program sa 2023 naman socio-economic program. Pero as to budget, pareho. Yes
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: or no?
Gina F. Acosta: Pareho, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: As to expected outcome? Pareho.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. Now, let's go to this physical target naman. In the 2023 physical plan, same observation ba, ma'am? Na nakasulat dyan, letter A, number, identified areas with surveillance conducted and monitored without, hindi po nakasulat dyan yung aktual na numero. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Same with the letter B entry. Percentage. Nakasulat dyan. Percentage. The symbol symbolizing percentage of activities implemented without and toward security-related incidents without stating the actual percentage. Tama po ba? Walang number.
Gina F. Acosta: Walang number. Tama po, Your Honor. In
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: fact, you admitted, Madam, In the 2020, in the November 25, 2024 Committee on Good Government Hearing, that you have to consult Colonel La Chica on what to put in the physical and financial plan. Do you remember this?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yan. The programs, yung programa po, yung mga ine-expect natin resulta sa mga programa, Yung mga targets ng mga plano, lahat ng ito ay gawa ay galing kay Colonel La Chica de Puba.
Gina F. Acosta: I will
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: repeat. Ang programa sa plano, ang expected outcome, ang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: target sa physical plan,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: galing. Kay Colonel Lachika. Tama po ba?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: objection? What's the objection, counsel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: As can be answered, Your Honor, the witness has already testified previously that security officers is providing inputs and
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: guidance, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: This is 2023, Your Honor. I think the question pertains to 2023 now. That was answered with respect to 2022. Ma'am Gina, yung nangyari po ba noong 2022, ganun din po sa 2023, galing kay Colonel Lachika?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa paggawa ng physical financial plan, Your Honor, kasama kaya po na ko siya. Kasama ko siya, Your Honor. Sa kanya pa rin ako nanghingi ng inputs and guidelines po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So galing nga po sa kanya. Galing kay Colonel Atchika yung inyong inputs na nilagay dito.
Gina F. Acosta: Kaming dalawa po, Your Honor, ang nag-discuss, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel, your witness. Let's go to that November 25, 2024 hearing. Ma'am. Tinanong ka ni Representative Jean K. Luistro. As a matter of fact, the financial plan does not bear at all the signature or the name of Colonel La Chica. Ma'am, yung sagot niyo diyan. Yes po. Pero sa kanya po ako humihingi ng inputs or information with regards to the implementation of all these projects included in the confidential funds. This is what you said under oath in November 25. 2024, under oath. Tama po ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor, please. Ma'am, did you answer opo?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Opo, ma'am. Your Honor, it's 12. Can I ask one
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: question? And I move for lunch break? Yes, counsel. Before we proceed to the next question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ito yung tanong na aw.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, sir. Ay, it's attorney. Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa lahat ng mga dokumento, isinumitin nyo sa COA, Commission on Audit. The plan, accomplishment reports,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: liquidation
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: reports.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nakasaad ba dyan sa kahit anong dokumento? Yung sinasabi nyo na lahat ng inputs yung sinulat nyo sa plano, lahat ng inputs sinulat nyo sa reporting to COA. Nakasaad ba dyan yung pangalan ni Colonel Lachica? Direction,
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor. The document would speak for itself, Your Honor. That's a
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: question
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the public is very much willing to hear.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer. Counsel, let the witness answer. I think she knows the answer anyway.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama ba pag-understand ko sa question mo, Your Honor, na sa lahat ng mga dokumento na isubmit ko sa... Plano,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: physical plan, ma'am. Physical
Gina F. Acosta: plan. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sa accomplishment report
Gina F. Acosta: mismo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sa liquidation report,
Gina F. Acosta: sa
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: certification na successful yung paggamit, tama yung paggamit ng plano. May isang dokumento ba dun? Ma'am, limited po tayo dun ha? Na ipinakita nyo sa publiko na si Curdel Lachica yung nagbibigay sa'yo ng input sa mga plano, saka siya yung nag-implement ng mga programs, activities. Meron ba dun? Yes? or no.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Move for
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: lunch
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: break, Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina, kain muna tayo para makahinga at relax kayo. Sige po.
Gina F. Acosta: Mas better po, attorney. Ay,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Okay lang po, ma'am. Huwag kayong mag-alala dun. Pahinga muna kayo. Kain tayo. The court will declare a lunch recess. We shall resume at 12.45.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Trial
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: is resumed. For the information of the counsel for the parties, we shall only be holding trial given the inclement weather until 2 p.m. this afternoon and we shall convene session according to the Senate President
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: at
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 2.30 p.m. So kindly be aware of the time, Atty. Ligutan, and if at all we reach cross, kindly be aware of the time.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina? Patuloy po kayo magtetestigo sa ilalim ng pareho niyong pinanumpaan kanina. Naunawaan niyo po iyon? Opo,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay. Atty. Ligutan, your witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hello.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Marami Tess, now, kanina nabanggit mo na si Colonel La Chica yung nagbibigay sa iyo ng inputs. Ano yung isusulat sa plano? at saka sa liquidation saka accomplishment reports. Kanina rin, the record will bear me out, in fact, nasabi mo rin, na siya rin yung may alam sa pag-i-implement ng mga sinasabi nyong confidential activities na pinagagamitan ng confidential funds. Now, yung tanong now is, Ma'am, empleyado ba, empleyado ba ng Office of the Vice President si Colonel Achica?
Gina F. Acosta: Siya po ang itinalaga na security officer ng Office of the Vice President, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung tanong, I think, is simple.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina, pag sinabi niyong security, sagot niyo po kanina, siya ang commanding officer ng VPSPG. Sinabi niyo rin po na siya ang security officer ng OVP. Meron po ba siyang appointment at sweldong tinatanggap bilang security officer ng OVP? Wala po.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi ko po alam, Your Honor, kung may sahod po siya. Pero ang alam ko, meron po siyang office order na siya po ang security officer ng Office of the Vice President. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your witness, counsel?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I think the question is simple, ma'am. Sa alam niyo, sa pagkakaalam niyo, I'm not asking ano yung designation niya. I think you are more than competent to answer this question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Impliyado ba ng Office of the Vice President? Si Colonel Achica.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Asking and answered, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: answer yet. Witness will answer, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kung alam niyo po, ma'am.
Gina F. Acosta: Ang alam ko po, siya po ang security officer, Your Honor. Yung lang po, ang alam ko.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That was his answer, counsel. Her answer, rather. Alright, now. Madam
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness, I'm showing you now yung isang letter. Galing sa office of the Vice President, May Pichang, November 30, 2023. Pirmado ng isang Lemuel Ortonio.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: We
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: are confronting you with the documents through authority and the letter is also being shown on our screen.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Assistant
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Councils may approach.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, kindly
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: zoom in to the relevant person.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: According to this letter, ma'am,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: November 30, 2023.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nakasulat dyan na as early as July 2022,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: yung OVP nakapag-identify na ng mga programa tsaka surveillance activities na sinasabi dyan intertwined with matters of national security. Yung letter is dated November 30, 2023.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pero nakasulat dyan as early as July 2022, nakapag-identify ng mga programa. Aware ka ba sa letter na ito?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Aware ka hindi?
Gina F. Acosta: Aware po ako,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: in fact, aware ka rin na itong letter na ito, ito yung tugon, reply ng OVP through Ortonio sa Audit Observation Memorandum. Aware ka rin yan, di ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: based sa letter na ito ma'am, programs at surveillance activities na sinasabi niyo intertwined with national security, eh sinasabi niyo na-identify na as early as July 2022 and you will agree with me ma'am eh kung July pa lang 2022.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor,
Gina F. Acosta: saan po dito
Gina F. Acosta: Sinabi mo na activities, Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, nasa screen. These programs, program goals are indistricably intertwined with matters of national security.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: July
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 22. Assistant counsel, kindly point it out
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: on page 2.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Page 2.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly point it out to the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What counsel is referring to?
Gina F. Acosta: Sir, ano po yung question? Yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: tanong now is, hindi ba dapat? Isinama niyo ito, yung mga sinasabi niyo mga specific activities sa physical and financial plan for the fourth quarter 2022 which is dated December 13, 2022. Isinama niyo ba yan?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Argumentative, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Repraise, counsel. I get the point of the objection of the counsel. Sustained. Okay, now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: po ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Those should have been reflected in the physical and financial plan for the fourth part of 2022. Same objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina, bakit di niyo po sinama yung mga bagay na yan doon sa physical and financial plan ng 2022? Kung Julyo pa lang, may ganyan na pala, bakit hindi niyo po yan sinama? Sa 2022 physical and financial plan.
Gina F. Acosta: Sir,
Gina F. Acosta: ito po ba yung target property alleviation treats to peace and order and the promotion of economic development po?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel? I think the public knows whether the witnesses answered the question or not. I will move on, Your Honor, please. Move forward, Counsel. Thank you. Now, Madam. Let's go to this cash encashment for the check-in cashment para sa 2022 Confidential Funds. Now, pinapakita sa iyo ngayon yung isang cheque, May-Pechang, December 20, 2022.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay? As well as yung nasa likod ng checking iyan. Okay? Yung checking yan has been previously marked as Exhibit PI-28, small letter A, and PI-28, small letter A-1.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung tanong, you personally encashed, ikaw mismo yung nag-encash ng 125 million pesos cash advance ng confidential funds noong December 20, 2022, correct?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And then, ma'am, na-encash mo yan only pagkatapos yung cheque maibigay sa iyo. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tanong, kailan ba na-encash yung cheque nito? Diba, December 20, 2022?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: And hindi po ba, bago ma-release yung cheque sa iyo, Yung checking iyan, kailangan munang i-prepara at saka dapat pirmado ng chief accountant. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Ah, nag-perma po?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: No, ma'am. The question is, tama po ba na bago nyo ma-relate, bago nyo natanggap yung checking, yung checking iyan, kailangan i-prepare muna at saka pirmahan.
Gina F. Acosta: I
Gina F. Acosta: -prepare po ng accountant po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes. Okay now. And of course, madam, yung checking iyan, Naprepare lang, napirmahan lang, na-release sa'yo lang only after the required disbursement voucher had been signed and approved. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If you can remember, ma'am, yung disbursement voucher napirmahan tsaka na-approved same day, December 20, 2022. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yung date ng voucher at saka date ng cheque. On
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: the same day?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: In fact, yun yung disbursement voucher dated December 20, 2022, Exhibit P, I-10A. Now, yung voucher na iyan, firmado ng VP Sara Duterte, Julieta Villadil Rey, tsaka Lemuel Ortonio. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, di ko ma... Mabasa yung after my name
Gina F. Acosta: kung orto
Gina F. Acosta: niyo
Gina F. Acosta: po
Gina F. Acosta: ayon.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly furnish Gina a copy of the disbursement voucher.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: It's in her possession at the moment, Your Honor, please.
Gina F. Acosta: Voucher.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Disbursement voucher for the last quarter of 2022, Ma'am Gina.
Gina F. Acosta: Claro po yung perma dito. Ang maklaro ko lang dito, Your Honor, is may perma po, signature, and then may perma po dito ng accountant namin.
Gina F. Acosta: Pero
Gina F. Acosta: yung sa gitna, hindi po kasi claro dito, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Move on,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: counsel. Now, madam, yung disbursement voucher, yung pag-pre-prepare, pag-peperma, tsaka pag-re-release ng cheque, yung date ng cheque, tsaka yung pag-i-incast ng cheque, they all happened on the same day, December 20, 2022. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: How much was the amount incast on that day? 125 million pesos, di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You incast this cheque sa Land Bank Shaw Boulevard Branch. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, listen to this question now. For unusual amounts like 125 million pesos, yung bangko kailangan inotify, manotify yung bangko isang araw minimum or at least two days before ma-encash yung cheque para ma-prepare, maihanda yung cash. Ito yung na-mention ni Ms. Violeta Constantino. Then, Department Manager ng Land Bank Show Boulevard, when she testified, do you confirm this practice? Objection,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. What's
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: the objection?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: The question is misleading, Your Honor. There's no testimony as to unusual amount, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: There was, counsel. There was. There was, counsel. Not by
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: the witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Not by this witness, but by the Land Bank Executive.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Hindi po ba? Kailangan mo notify muna yung bangko a
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: day or two? May we ask the prosecution to repeat the question, Your Honor? I think
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: there was a ruling. If
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: she knows. Yes. Ma'am Gina, kayo po ba yung nag-i-inform sa bangko o may kailangan po ba mag-i-inform sa bangko na mag-i-withdraw kayo ng ganito kalaking pera?
Gina F. Acosta: Ganito po, Your Honor. Nang handa na po ang cheque, tumawag po ang aming cast division. Now, ma'am Gina, handa na po ang cheque at pwede mo nang ipaincast sa bangko.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Not responsive? Okay. Now, continue counsel. Now, by what time did you go to land bank? On December 20, 2022?
Gina F. Acosta: Mga around 2 to 2.30, nakaabot din to, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 2 to 2.30, hindi 3 p.m.?
Gina F. Acosta: Mga ganyan na, Your Honor. Your Honor, witness
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: already answered. Wait, wait, time to clarify because that's what he said in the hearing. Anyway, so it's 2, 2.30 and then when confronted with another option, 3pm, yung sagot mo, mga ganyan. So it includes 3pm. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Basta, naabot ko dito, Your Honor, mga 2 to 2.30. Alright,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: now, by the time you arrived at the bank on December 20, 2022, yung 125 million pesos in cash, Nakahanda na, di po ba, for your withdrawal?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa pagkaalam ko, nakahanda na kasi tumawag po ang aming cash division, Your Honor, na kunin ko na ang cheque at pwede na ding ipain-cash sa bangko. Yes.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ibig sabihin, at least, nanotify ng opisina nyo yung land bank a day before December 20, 2022 na mag-i-cash kayo ng gandong kahalaking Halaga, 125 million pesos sa araw na iyan, December 20, 2022. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tama po. Now, meaning, yung
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: land bank na-notify na, na ihanda yung 125 million pesos bago pa man ma
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: -aprubahan ang disbursement voucher bago pa man maihanda. Matirmahan, tsaka marilis ang cheque sa inyo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: about informing the bank before the voucher or checks were prepared.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, anyways, Your Honor, please, we'll move to the next points.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Voucher was signed, prepared, check was signed, prepared, released to you on the same day.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, hindi ba iyon?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pagfa-fast-track.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pagfa-fast-track na pag-iin-cash ng 125 million pesos. on the same day.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Vague and argumentative.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overruled. Witness may answer. Court would like to know her answer.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi ba minadali?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung pagdi-disbursement voucher, pag-premipara ng cheque, pag-i-encash, on the same day, 125,000,000 pesos. Yes or no?
Gina F. Acosta: Dumaan po siya sa regular na proseso namin sa office, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Being vague again. Now. As the SDO and Project Accountable Officer, hindi po ba na yung pagmamadaling yan, ikaw yung nag-utos yan? Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po ako nag-utos, Your Honor. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sino ang nag-utos sa inyo?
Gina F. Acosta: Basta gi-process po yun, Your Honor, on a regular processing po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma'am, ma'am, I think I have to repeat the question, Your Honor, because she did not answer the question. Minadali? May nag-utos? When asked, sino nag-utos? Sabi mo, hindi ikaw. I will ask this question again. Yung publiko are very much waiting for an answer. Sino ang nag-utos ng pagmamadali, ng pag-incash, ng checking yan, 125 million sa araw na yan?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Objection, Your Honor. Misleading. Objection is sustained again, counsel. There is no basis...
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pagkatapos ma-verify ng bank teller, yung identification at saka pagkatapos i-approve yung pag-i-incast ng checking iyan, di po ba you were instructed na magpunta sa backroom ng bangko? Objection,
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor. Misleading, Your Honor. The witness hasn't testified yet. I'm asking for confirmation. It
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: may be leading but it's okay to ask leading questions because this was testified to by another witness from land banks that she went to the backroom.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Just to clarify, Your Honor, the objection is grounded that it is misleading, Your Honor, because there's no testimony yet that any bank teller verified, Your Honor. There's no testimony yet from the witness, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: No testimony. He is asking the witness on the basis of the testimony given before the court council by a land bank official that Gina and... If I recall correctly, Colonel Latsika and Ortonio went to the back room of the bank. And the bank officer, in fact, if I remember correctly, testified that there was a door leading to the exit.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: To
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: another exit. Yes, Your Honor. Your Honor. That pertains to DepEd Council. Your Honor, that
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: may be the case, Your Honor, but it hasn't yet testified by the witness. With due respect to the prosecution, the proper basis must be laid, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Modify, modify, modify for this one, counsel. I stand corrected with respect to the backdoor testimony that it connected to DepEd. I distinctly remember that. Not with the OVP. I stand corrected. Backroom, backroom, Your Honor. I'm asking
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: for the backroom now. Is it it? Is it it? Okay. In that afternoon, you were instructed... to the back room of the bank. Di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Ano po yun? Back room, bank
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: room. Back room po, back room.
Gina F. Acosta: Sorry po, sorry po, sir. It's
Gina F. Acosta: okay. Sorry
Gina F. Acosta: po.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Attorney Ligudan, kwarto sa likod o banyo? Kwarto sa likod.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala pong kwarto sa likod, Your Honor. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: okay. Okay now. The question is simple.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Saan nyo nakita? yung 125 million pesos na in-cash niyo sa araw na iyon sa loob ng bangko.
Gina F. Acosta: Doon po sa may likod niyang, Taylor, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now. Sa likod ng...
Gina F. Acosta: Open space po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Sa likod ng...
Gina F. Acosta: Taylor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Taylor. Now, ma'am, can you describe for us, to give us a mental picture, how big the pile?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 125 million pesos in cold cash is.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ipa-describe.
Gina F. Acosta: Sorry, Sir, ha? Pero hindi kaya ko well-versed sa mga measure-measurement. Pero nakasulod siya sa nakalagay siya sa box na nakabandal tag 1 million ang isa kabandal na nakaputos, nakabalot. o xilophen na xilyo pa, xilyado pa.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sinasabi mo ma'am, hindi ka well-versed sa measurement. Tama po ba? Di ba? Now, I will show you a simulated representation of 125 million pesos. Sinabi mo 1,000 peso bill, di ba? Show that to the screen, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I'm sorry.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You tell the public, ma'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: If yung nakita mong 125 million pesos in cold cash, Your Honor, Wait, wait, wait, natin dyan, natin dyan, natin dyan.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, to finish the question, Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Bacuel,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can you please confirm if the cold cash you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: saw,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 125 million pesos, do they look like that?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, before the prosecution proceeds with the question, may we just ask as to the source of the photo and how it was generated and produced?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yes, counsel, either it is distorted because the 1,000 peso bills look bigger.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Is this AI, Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, of course, that is simulated.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Is
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: this AI? because we don't have 125 million pesos in cold cash. So we have to resort to technology.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Is that, Your Honor, artificial intelligence? Is this AI? Yes. Generated? Yes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel, if you will allow the presiding officer. Ma'am Gina, sabi niyo nakalagay po sa kahon tigi isan libong bundle. Ilang kahon po?
Gina F. Acosta: Dalawa, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Gaano kalaki po yung kahon?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Limitin niyo po yung kamay niyo.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Gano'ng kataas po?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Gano'ng kataas?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung kamay niyo po sa baba, pakipat yan para makita po namin. Ganyan kataas at ganito kalapad? Kasing lapad po ng witness stand?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 125 million po yan. Dalawang kahong ganyan.
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Binilang niyo po ba? Tinanggal niyo po ba mula sa kahon? O hindi na?
Gina F. Acosta: Tinanggal po sa kahon, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pagkatanggal niyo sa kahon, binilig niyo ba sa kahon?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Saan niyo na nilagay?
Gina F. Acosta: Nilagay ko po sa aking apat na bag.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ito po yung daffle bag.
Gina F. Acosta: Parang traveling bag po, Your Honor, na oblong.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Traveling bag, apat pong gano'n?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Procedure,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Witness, Counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sinabi mo, ma'am, na iyong 125 million pesos naka-bundle. into 1,000 peso bills. Sa isa kang bundle is 1 million pesos. Again, para sa ating mga kababayan na hindi pa nakakita, how does a 1 million buy this? Counsel, is that an actual
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: thing again or a reproduction?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Reproduction.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your Honor.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Yes, while you're showing the witness, Attorney Bachel. May we just interpose an objection as regards presenting the witness those props, Your Honor, inasmuch as the parties are uncertain, the defense is uncertain as to how is that an accurate representation of what the prosecution claims to be, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I will ask. I will ask the question, Your Honor, please.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Before I rule on the objection, yes, counsel, ask your question. and kindly don't cover Ms. Gina.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: so
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sorry.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ma
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 'am, sinabi mo, yung 125 billion pesos nakapile by 1 million peso each, tama po ba? Opo. And then, yung bills ginamit is 1,000. Tama po ba? Sinabi mo, hindi ka well-versed sa measurement. Doon sabi mo, di ba? Kaya nga, eto yung simulated.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ten bundles. The size is similar to 1,000 peso bills. Ma'am, yung isang milyon, pwede niyo pong hawakan if you want. If you want lang, ha? May lagi dagal, ma'am, ha? Now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung 1,000,000 pesos, kamukha ba ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: isang bundle na ito?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Your Honor. Wait, wait. Is that your question, Atty. Higutan? Yes. Yes, Atty. Bagel.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, we manifest that upon the examination of assisting counsel, these appear to be just blue-colored lengthwise papers wrapped in plastic with 10 bundles each. How is this an accurate representation of... The size of whatever the prosecution claims to be, Your Honor, they are yet to lay the proper basis as regards this, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Counsel claims it's a mere simulation. If that is an objection, counsel, I will have to overrule the objection. Witness will please answer. Ma'am, parang ganyan po ba yung bundle ng tigay isang libong pinitraw ninyo?
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, may I know po kung ito po ay... Is this...
Gina F. Acosta: 100,000? Yes. Is this 100,000?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sa pagkakaalala niyo po kung tagi isang libo po yan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Sampung bundle ng tagi isang libo na ang kabuhuan ay isang milyon sa isang balot ng plastic. Ganyan po ba yung itsura ng inyong winidraw? Yung bundle po ha, yung bundle.
Gina F. Acosta: Basta nakabalot lang po siya ng silupin, Your Honor, tapos binilang po namin.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am, when you
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: say silupin, plastic. Plastic.
Gina F. Acosta: Ito, ito, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kaya nga, so ganyan po yung size. Oo,
Gina F. Acosta: nakasilyo po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Bagong pera po ba, lumang pera?
Gina F. Acosta: Bagong pera po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay, so mga ganyan nga po yung size. Yun lang ang tinatanong sa inyo ni Attorney Ligutan. Huwag natin pag-usapan yung bigat, yung hugis. We'll go into the weight later.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Halos ganyan po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Ganito po, Your Honor. Basta nakabalut po siya ng silupin.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am, kayo naman. Makita niyo naman kung halos parehas eh. Para halos parehas mo ba? Yan lang ganun kasimple yung tanaw.
Gina F. Acosta: May similarity, Your Honor. May manggot siya. Lapad-lapad man ang kwarta.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay. Thank you, Your Honor. Now, Madam Witness, ilan
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: yan? 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 1,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, 125 of these bundles, correct? Yung nakita niyo sa hapon na iyon, December 20, 2022, tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yun
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: yung nakita niyo sa bangko na in-cash ng Office of the Vice President, cash, cold cash, sa hapon na iyon, tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Ano po? 125 million po ito, Your Honor, ang nakita na ko, namang giihap. Gibilang po namin, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Just to clarify, Gina, before Atty. Backel, before I recognize you, bundle count lang po ang ginawa niyo.
Gina F. Acosta: Bundle count po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi niyo na
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: po binuksan yung cellophane na sinasabi niyo, yung plastic, binilang niyo na lang po, 125 yung gano'n.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi na po, Your Honor. Nakasilyo po kasi, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So, binilang niyo na lang po, 125 na gano'n.
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi na isa-isa.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi niyo na binilang isa-isa yung bill.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung tigil isang libo.
Gina F. Acosta: Atty.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Bakel, yes, what is your comment or objection?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, may we respectfully ask if the props could already be removed, Your Honor, as it's not necessary for the testimony of the witness.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: It is, Your Honor. Are you done yet with that, with your civilization counsel?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Not yet, Your
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Honor. Not yet. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wind
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: it up.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes. Now, I'm sure, Madam Witness, with your
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor, ibig sabihin pa kung sinong kasama ko pagpunta sa bangko?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sa loob ng bangko, kaharap yung 125 million pesos in cold cash. Sino yung kasama mo from the office of the Vice President kung meron man?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, before the Vice President may answer, Your Honor, the question of the prosecution is totally unrelated to the use of the props, Your Honor. May we just request, Your Honor, I'm still not finished. May we just respect, the defense respectfully requests, Your Honor, that these be removed until the relevant question is interposed, considering that the witness has the right to be respected as well.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wait, wait, wait.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I think I
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: see,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Bachel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I think the court sees, well, Atty. Ligutan is getting to, get to it, Atty. Ligutan. Yes, yes. Okay. Ms. Gina, may kasama po ba kayong ibang tao mula sa OVP noong pinick up niyo yung pera?
Gina F. Acosta: Meron po, Your Honor. Sino
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: po?
Gina F. Acosta: Si Asic or Tonyo po, Your Honor. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tony Lagutan, Your Witness. Okay, now, walang membro ng VPSPG. Okay, yung kasama niyo, yung Vice Presidential Special Protection Group, kasama niyo sa loob ng bangkong iyan. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, Your Honor, pero ang aming driver po ay member po ng VPSPG. Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ma'am. Now. Even with such large amount of money, hindi niyo naisipan na mag-request ng isang or maraming escorts na sasama sa inyo sa bangko tsaka lalabas with those bills. Tama po ba?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor. Argumentative.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overruled, counsel. Witness will answer.
Gina F. Acosta: Ang gisama ko po, Your Honor, nakisuyo po ako, nasamahan po ako ni Asik Ortonio.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ortonio lang. Nakiusap ka, nasamahan ka ni Asik Ortonio.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. How
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: did you bring out, out of the bank, that 125 million pesos?
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, pwede ulitin ang question.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, paano niyo inilabas ng banko? Yung 125 billion pesos na iyan.
Gina F. Acosta: May tumulong po sa akin, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay now, sino yung tumulong sa inyo?
Gina F. Acosta: Yung security ng land bank po, Your Honor. This
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: is the question now. Okay. Yung 125 billion pesos na iyan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Did
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you put it into bags or you brought them out one by one?
Gina F. Acosta: Nilagay po yun sa apat na bag, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Apat na bag. So hindi po hand-carry lang yung bills na yan.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So now we will give in to what the defense wants, Your Honor, please. Having been satisfied that this person cannot bring out of the bank using her own two hands. These bills, no, we can now. Attorney Jay? Assistant counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Proceed, counsel. Okay, now. You said you put them sa mga traveling bags. Ilang bags? Apat po, diba?
Gina F. Acosta: Apat, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Can you describe to us yung size ng mga traveling bags na ito?
Gina F. Acosta: Ganito, Your Honor. Paoblong.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, paoblong. I will show you now representation of 125 million pesos inside four traveling bags.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ito yung tanong now.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, four traveling bags with bills, 1,000 peso bills inside them. Yung hapon na iyon ma'am, maalala niyo ba Miss Gina F. Acosta? kung yung nawithdraw nyo na 125 million pesos na isinilit nyo sa four traveling bags, do they look like this? Before you answer, Gina,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: for respondent?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, we interpose the same objection as regards the use of AI-generated imagery, Your Honor, without laying the proper basis as to how it's... It accurately represents what the prosecution claims to be, Your Honor. It has no basis, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: The court will simply note the objection of counsel. And counsel, the court will also take note of your continuing objection with respect to the use of AI-generated representations of what he is asking the witness about. If it shows closely or not. What bag she used to bring out the 125 million.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: With
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: your permission, counsel, court will note your continuing objection, the use of AI representations. Thank you, Your Honor. Counsel, witness will please answer. Ma'am Gina, parang ganyan po ba yung apat na bag na pinaglagyan niyo?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi ganyan, Your Honor, kasi ang opening niyan is round.
Gina F. Acosta: Ang sa akin, ang dinala ko po na bag is pa ganun po ang zipper.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Buo, pahaba, yung kabuoan ng bag. Okay, number one, yun ang isang pagkakaiba. Kulay?
Gina F. Acosta: Kulay black.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pareho.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: At apat na bag, kumasa yung 125.
Gina F. Acosta: Apat po na bag, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: thank you so much. Ma'am, in putting the bills inside the bag, okay, sino ba yung tumulong? Sa paglalagay ng mga bills, yung 1,000 peso bills sa mga bags na ito, sino yung gumawa niyan?
Gina F. Acosta: Ako po, Your Honor, ang naglagay ng mga pera sa bag.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: May membro pa ng VPSPG na tumulong sa iyo sa paglalagay ng mga bills na iyan sa bag?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, Your Honor. How
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: long did it take? for you to put all the 125 million pesos into the bags.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi ko maalala, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Maaalala niyo po ba? Kasi sa'yo kayo naglagay doon. Maaalala niyo po ba gaano ba kabigat yung isang bag containing piles of 1,000 peso bills piled into 1 million each?
Gina F. Acosta: Basta mabigat po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: What about 30 kilograms per bag. Kung maalala mo.
Gina F. Acosta: Di ko exactly maalala, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright. Ikaw ba ay nagkarga ng isa sa mga four bags na ito?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, Your Honor. So,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sino yung nagkarga?
Gina F. Acosta: Bali, ganito po. Ang pera ay nandiyo na sa lahat na pinanailagay na po sa apat
Gina F. Acosta: na bag.
Gina F. Acosta: Sa diyang onawal na ilabas ko na po, Your Honor, tumulong po sa akin ang dalawang security guard, Your Honor, ginano nila, Your Honor,
Gina F. Acosta: papunta sa
Gina F. Acosta: entrance ng bangko, kung saan, naghintay po ang aming sasakyan, Your Honor. Tapos ako, Your Honor, nagsunod, nagtanaw sa duwaka security, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright, now, what about Libel Ortonio? Ano ba yung ginawa niya kung meron man?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sa paglalabas ng four bags containing 125 million pesos in gold cash, may naitulong ba si ginoong Lemuel Ortonio?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wala. Again, walang escorts, no request for escort, di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, pero ang amoang driver, Your Honor, is a member of BPSBG.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Isang driver?
Gina F. Acosta: Duhay, Your Honor,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: dalawang. Two
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: drivers. Okay. Aside from these two drivers, yung tanong ko is, aside from the two drivers, walang ibang membro ng BPSPG.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: As an answer, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: As an answer, counsel. What time did you leave the bank?
Gina F. Acosta: Ano, Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Anong oras kayo lumabas ng bangko?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi ko exactly maalala, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi mo maalala. Now, galing sa trolley, papunta ng mga sasakyan. Okay? Sino yung nag-transfer ng mga bags na yan?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Misleading, Your Honor. There's no testimony as to the trolley. I did hear trolley
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: as well,
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I will
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: reform, Your Honor. Now, sino ba yung nag-transfer galing sa bangko papuntahan sa sasakyan ng
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: four bags na yan?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Ask and answer, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Atty. Gina, with the indulgence of counsels, sabi niyo wala kayong binuwat sa apat na bag. Tama po.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Wala rin binuhat si Ginong Ortonio sa apat na bag.
Gina F. Acosta: Wala sab, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ang nagbuhat, dalawang security guard ng bangko.
Gina F. Acosta: Sila po ang tumulong. Sila, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tig dalawang bag ang binuhat nila o may trolley silang ginamit?
Gina F. Acosta: Di kaya ko ka-remember kung nagamit sila o trolley. Ang ma-remember ko, Your Honor, gi-drag nila ang dua ka bag.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Dalawang bag kada guard.
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Isahang labasan yung apat na bag.
Gina F. Acosta: Sabay po sila, Your Honor, at nandun po ako, Your Honor, nagsunod-sunod sa ilan, nagtanaw, Your Honor. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Your witness, counsel. Now, so, paano ninyo, transfer, dinala, yung four bags na yan galing Land Bank Show Boulevard papunta sa pinuntahan nyo after that?
Gina F. Acosta: Gisakay. Sinakay sa? Amo ang service, Your Honor? Service.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Pag sinabing service, ibig niyong sabihin, sasakyan.
Gina F. Acosta: Opo.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ilang sasakyan kung meron man?
Gina F. Acosta: Dalawa, Your Honor. Kaninong
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: sasakyan yung pinagsidlan, pinagsakyan ng perang iyan?
Gina F. Acosta: Sa OBP, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: OBP. Sumakay ka ba sa similar sa parehong sasakyan together with Lemuel Ortonio?
Gina F. Acosta: Ako nagsakay sa isang sasakyan, Your Honor. Tapos si Ortonio po nagsakay sa isang sasakyan, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Cal, saan kayo nagpunta after that?
Gina F. Acosta: Nagpunta po kami sa office po ng OBP.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Office of the Vice President. Anong oras kayo dumating doon, if at all?
Gina F. Acosta: Mga, nakaabot mo dito mga 4 o 4 o 'clock
Gina F. Acosta: ng konti.
Gina F. Acosta: 4 plus ng hapon.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: 4 plus ng hapon. Who assisted you, kung meron man, in transferring the bags from the cars to the office of the Vice President? Kung meron man.
Gina F. Acosta: Pagdating ko doon sa Fort Lawyer, Your Honor, sa office po kasi namin, meron pong talagang naka-duty na mga BPSPG.
Gina F. Acosta: So,
Gina F. Acosta: naka-arrive na kami sa Fort Lawyer, Your Honor. Open ang car, tapos nakita ng BPSPG na nag-action ako na kunin ang bag. Nakita nila na dili ko kaya. Tumulong po ang dalawang BPSPG, Your Honor,
Gina F. Acosta: na
Gina F. Acosta: ang bag makuha doon sa sasakyan, tapos ilagay namin sa trolley. Tapos sakay na kami, Your Honor, sa elevator na hindi tao ang sumasakay. Service elevator, Your Honor. Saan niyo
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: dinala yung pera?
Gina F. Acosta: Dinala ko po sa aking extension office, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yung four traveling bags?
Gina F. Acosta: Opo, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ito yung tanong now, Madam Witness. Hindi po ba, noong November 25, 2024, Committee on Good Government and Public Accountability hearing, sinabi niyo dun, please show the TSN.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That's right after encashment, pagkatapos pong ma-encash yung 125 million pesos, tinawagan mo sino?
Gina F. Acosta: CSO officer, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Colonel Lachika.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: To
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: quote, sinabi mo dun, you called him and you told him na eto na yung ready na yung 125 million pesos. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Sinabihan ko po siya, Your Honor, na na-encast ko na po ang chike for the confidential funds.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes, ma'am. Question. Ikaw yung specialist bursing officer. Ikaw yung nag-prepare ng confidential at yung physical financial plan. Hindi mo masabi kung empleyado ba. Hindi mo masagot-sagot yung napakasimpleng tanong kung empleyado ba si Colonel La Chica. The question is, why?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Did you have to call Colonel La Chica to inform him? Colonel La Chica, ready na. 125 million pesos. Bakit?
Gina F. Acosta: Kasi po, may instruction po sa taas, Your Honor, ng aking head of agency na kung ma-encash ko po ang cheque, i-release ko po kay Sir La Chica kinsa ihangi-designate na special officer po. As security officer po sa office of the Vice President, na as I order, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, ma'am. Sabi mo, tinawagan mo si Colonel Achica kasi yun yung utos ng head of agency. Siguro sa ating mga kababayan na hindi alam, sino ba?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Sino ba ang head of agency na nag-utos sa'yo as the special disbursing officer na ibigay? Yung 125 million pesos in cold cash sa isang security officer, Colonel Raymond Dante Lachica.
Gina F. Acosta: Ang nag-utos po sa akin na i-release ang pera na 125M sa security officer na si Colonel Lachica ay si Ma'am Sara Duterte.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You turned over 125 million pesos to Col. La Chica precisely para siya yung mag-disburse ng 125 million pesos for the supposed confidential activities ng Office of the Vice President. Tama po ba?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Misleading, Your Honor. What?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Why is it misleading, counsel?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, the witness has yet to testify on anything but the question. is premised on Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Overruled, counsel. Witness said that she was instructed by the head of agency, the vice president, to give the money to... Anong word ginamit niya, ma'am? Transfer?
Gina F. Acosta: Release.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Release. To release the money to Colonel Lachica. Proceed, counsel. Now,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: hindi po ba na nag-testify ka rin sa November 25, 2024? Committee on Good Government Hearing na binigay mo yung 125 million pesos kay Curly La Chica kasi si La Chica lang yung may alam, siya lang yung may alam on how to implement yung confidential activities. Di po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes po. Siya po
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ang expert. You can explain po later, ma'am. And you only came to know that Colonel La Chica knows how to implement the confidential activities. Nalaban nyo lang na si Colonel La Chica yung may alam paano i-implement yung confidential activities precisely because yun yung sabi sa inyo ni VP Inday Sara Duterte. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Kasi po ang
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: security. With all due respect po, pupwede pong sagutin ng yes or no without... Explain, explanation. Ma'am, I will allow you. Pero po ba, puwede po bang sagutin po muna? Yes or no? I will allow you to explain.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, the witness is answering, Your Honor. May the witness be allowed to finish her answer?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: She already started answering, counsel. Let her answer and you can continue with your direct. Kindly answer. Pakisagot po, Ma'am Gina. Yung katanungan.
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, may I request to repeat the question, Your Honor?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Ulit na lang
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: po, Atty. Niligutan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Nalaman mo na si Colonel La Chica yung may alam paano i-implement yung confidential activities. Kasi nga, yun yung sabi sa inyo ni VP Sara Duterte. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, siya po ang security officer na sinabi ni Vice Presidente.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Alright, now, I'm showing you yung transcript, page 140 this time.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Do we have it? Page 140.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tanong sa inyo, Representative Luizo, then why did you give all the money to Colonel La Chica? Yung sagot niyo was because po may utos po ni Ma'am Inday Sara na sa kanya po i-release kasi siya po ang nakakaalam kung paano po i-implement ang mga programs and activities in line po sa confidential activities. You confirm that?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Madam, since si La Chica yung may alam, paano i-implement yung project? under confidential funds, siya din yung nag-implement ng mga confidential activities. This time, ma'am, hindi na 2022. This time, for 2023, correct?
Gina F. Acosta: Same question, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay, I will repeat the question. Siyang sabi mo, ipinabigay ni VP Sara yung pera kay La Chica kasi siya yung may alam paano i-implement yung confidential activities. Okay now, yung tanong is, si Colonel La Chica din. yung nag-implement ng lahat ng confidential activities this time, ma'am, para sa taong 2023. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Tama po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, this is the question now. You will agree that handling tsaka yung pagdi-disperse ng 500 million pesos na pera ng bayan, ma'am, pondo ng bayan,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Hindi iyan trabaho ng isang security officer kagaya ni Colonel La Chica. Tama po ba?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: What's the objection? Counsel, what's the objection?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Your Honor, the objection is grounded that it's argumentative and it calls for a conclusion, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kindly modify, counsel. It is argumentative. You can modify and get the response you want from the witness. Yes,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ma'am. Yes, sir. Now, Madam Witness, hindi po pa na base sa paragraph 3.27 ng Joint Circular 2015. Please flash that one.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yun yung trabaho ng isang security officer. refers to a personnel who by reason of his duty or employment has been officially designated to have access to security information. Tanong, andyan ba dyan? Nakasulat na po puwedeng yung isang security officer yung mag-iimplement ng confidential activities tsaka yung mag-de-disperse ng confidential funds ng isang ahensya. like the office of the Vice President.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Same objection, Your Honor. Argumentative and calls for a conclusion.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: If she knows, counsel, because she answered that she based her actions based on JC 2015-1. Ma'am Gina, pakisagot po yung tanong. Bahagi po ba ng trabaho ng security officer ayon sa Joint Circular ang tumanggap ng confidential at mag-implement ng confidential funds?
Gina F. Acosta: Siya po ang may alam, siya po ang expert to Your Honor sa pagpatupad po ng confidential operation and activities, Your Honor. Kasi siya po ang may access when it comes to national security, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ayon po kanino, ma'am? Ayon sa Joint Circular, ayon sa interpretation niyo, o ayon sa utos sa inyo?
Gina F. Acosta: Ayon po sa Joint Circular, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Saan po sa Joint Circular, alam niyo po? At
Gina F. Acosta: saka ayon po sa utos ng head of agency kasi meron po siyang security officer na order, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel, your witness. Of course, iisa-isahin natin yan. Sinabi mo nasa Joint Circular, yung basihan, na po pwede yung security officer, okay, gumamag-disperse ng confidential funds. Ma'am, I will give you. all the time you will need. Basahin. 2015. Circular. Saan dyan? Saan dyan makikita? Yung sinasabi mong puwedeng security officer yung magkasta disbursed ng confidential funds.
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor, based po sa aking nalalaman sa GC, ako po ang special disbursing officer. Ang gawain ko po, Your Honor, is... to this board. Pero ang pag-implement po ng mga confidential operation activities in related to confidential funds, yan po ay saklaw po sa trabaho po ng isang security officer kasi wala po akong alam. Well, di ako expert to Your Honor sa pagpatupad ng various Confidential activities or operations on the grounds, Your Honor. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I will tailor, I mean, I'll make this narrower. Yung pag-de-disperse, yung pagbabayan, paggagamit ng confidential funds, based sa circular, trabaho ba yan ng isang security officer?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: As you answered, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Overruled. Overruled. Witness will please answer.
Gina F. Acosta: Ano po yan?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Trabaho po ba ng isang dispersing, ng isang security officer yung paggamit ng confidential funds, pag-disperse ng confidential funds? Trabaho po ba iyan based on circular?
Gina F. Acosta: Basta ang trabaho ko, Your Honor, ako po ang dispersing officer, Your Honor, ang pagpa-implement po ng various confidential activities in relation po sa confidential funds, Your Honor, ay saklaw po sa trabaho ng security officer, Your Honor, kasi
Gina F. Acosta: confidential
Gina F. Acosta: po yun, Your Honor. Ma
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: 'am Gina, ang tanong po, trabaho ba ng security officer, gas to send, i-release, i-labas yung confidential fund na dinisverse po ninyo?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Kung oo po, saan sa joint circular nakalaga yun?
Gina F. Acosta: Ano yun, Sir?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Trabaho po ba ng security officer, gas to send, yung ni-release yung confidential fund? Iba po yung implement. Siyempre siya yung magagawa ng surveillance. Siyempre siya po yung kukuha ng mga operative na yun sa intelligence. Pero yung paggastos po. Trabaho po ba ng security officer gastusin yung dinisburst ninyong confidential fund?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po, Your Honor. Trabaho po yan ng disbursing officer, Your Honor. Pero pag nai-release ko na po ang pera sa kanya, Your Honor, pinareceive ko sa kanya, Your Honor, magbigay po siya sa akin ng utilization report, Your Honor. Yun po ang signed or evidenced, Your Honor, na gawa, na-implement na po niya, Your Honor, ang mga various confidential activities or operations, Your Honor, sa ground kasi siya po ang expert, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: So sa pananaw po ninyo, ang ginamit niyo pong salita, release.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung pag-release po nyo ng pera, kay Colonel Lachica eh dapat i-liquidate na po niya yun?
Gina F. Acosta: I-liquidate po niya, Your Honor, after po matapos po ang pagpa-implement ng various confidential activities po sa ground, Your Honor, kasi siya po ang expert po, Your Honor. Pero
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: siya po ang gumastos ng pera sa iba't ibang nakatanggap ng confidential fund. Tama po.
Gina F. Acosta: Ano yun, Your Honor?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Siya po ang gumastos ng pera at nag-abot ng pera Sa iba't ibang pinagbigyan niya, base sa intelligence at confidential operations niya, tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Siya po, Your Honor, kasi siya po ang may alam kung paano po i-implement ang mga confidential operations activities, Your Honor, kasi confidential po, Your Honor, wala po ako alam.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: ba sangayon sa Joint Circular, kayo dapat ang nagdi-disperse direkta sa beneficiary o recipient?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi naman po sinabi, Your Honor, na ako ang magpunta doon sa ground, Your Honor, kasi wala po akong alam, Your Honor, kung ipapatupad, wala po akong security, wala po akong access, Your Honor, sa tinatawag na security information, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Huling katanungan po, kaugnan nito bago kay Paso kay Eterna Lagutan. Sa pananaw niyo po ba, sa pag-release niyo kay Colonel Lachica, recipient si Colonel Lachica ng confidential fund, o... Ginampanan po niya yung tungkulin niya sa pag-disperse lamang.
Gina F. Acosta: Ah, lalipo ko. I'm sorry. I'm
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: confused. Recipient po ba si Atty. Lachica, si Col. Lachica? O tagapagbigay lang siya ng perang ni-release niyo sa kanya?
Gina F. Acosta: Ah, wait.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yung pera po ba'y tinanggap ni Col. Lachica para sa sarili niya?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Tinanggap po niya para ipamigay sa ibang tao.
Gina F. Acosta: Tinagka po niyo, Your Honor, para po, Your Honor, sa mga gastusin in relation po sa pagpatupad ng confidential activities or operations, Your Honor, kasi siya po ang may alam, Your Honor, at saka confidential in nature po, Your Honor. So
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: sa pananaw po ninyo, hindi siya recipient, si Colonel Lachica.
Gina F. Acosta: Yun po ang explanation ko sa iyo kanina, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Hindi nga po siya recipient.
Gina F. Acosta: Dily, Your Honor. Okay.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Dily is hindi. Now, you sit. At
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: to yung niligutan. You said that you gave the 125 billion pesos to Colonel Achika. Siya yung nag-disperse. Sabi mo kanina, una, kasi yun yung nakasulat sa Joint Circular 2015-01. And then, sabi mo, and that not only that, sinabi mo rin, kasi yun yung utos ng head of agency, si VP Inday Sara. Now, you were asked, saan sa circular nakasulat? na puwedeng mag-disperse ng confidential funds. Isang security officer hindi mo mahanap. Tama po ba? Tama po ba, ma 'am?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no? This is a premise to the next question, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Witness may answer, counsel?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Pakisagot po, ma'am Gina.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Kung hindi niyo po naunawaan pa, ulit niyo po. Wala sa Circular 2015-01 nakasulat dyan na puwedeng si Colonel Achika as security officer yung mag-disperse ng confidential funds. Wala dyan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wala dyan. Yes or no?
Gina F. Acosta: Wala, Your Honor.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: So, therefore, we are left with only the remaining reason why you gave the confidential funds to Col. La Chica. Kasi, yan.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You said, yung pangalawang rason.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi, dalawang rason po ang ibig sabihin ko, sir. Okay,
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: ma'am, no question yet. Hindi po tayo nag-aaway.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: You gave. The 125 million pesos kasi utos ni VP Sara sa'yo. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Isa po yan sa rason, Sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Yes or no?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes. Despite
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: nothing in the
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: circular. Yes or no?
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Argumentative and ask and answer, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Please answer the question, Madam Witness. It's quite easy to answer.
Gina F. Acosta: Despite not being
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: in the circular na po pwedeng si La Chica yung mag-disperse ng confidential funds, binigay mo pa rin sa kanya. Tama po ba?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi na ko ihatag, Your Honor, kung wala siya gi-appoint ng security officer, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: That's her interpretation, counsel? Yes. That's her interpretation and reason why she gave it to Colonel La Chica? Or
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: is it because you cannot dare question? The Vice President's instruction.
Atty. Lindon Miguel C. Bacquel: Objection, Your Honor, argumentative.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I would sustain it because it was asked and answered already. She gave two reasons, counsel. Number one, that Colonel Lachica is the one who knows how to implement it. Tama po. And number two, dahil inutos sa kanya ng Vice President bilang Head of Agency. Tama po, Ma'am Gina?
Gina F. Acosta: Tama po, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Yan po yung dalawang rason ba't niya binigay kay Colonel Lachica.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, Your Honor. Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Now, Madam
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Witness.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: I'm showing you now a video where
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: you said you entrusted the confidential funds in the amount of 125 million pesos to a security officer because the vice president directed you to do so and you merely complied. Can we play that?
Gina F. Acosta: Comply?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Wait po, wala pa po? Wala pang question?
Gina F. Acosta: Sorry, sorry po. It's
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: okay po. No need to be sorry po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Counsel,
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you have three minutes. Is this your last question for the afternoon?
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: For this afternoon. Let's play it.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: And then, since part of your job as a special disbursing officer is the disbursement of this amount, please enlighten us. Paano niyo po ginastos, ipinayad, inirelease itong 125 million pesos?
Gina F. Acosta: Ganito po ang nangyari, ma'am. Nang ma-encash na po ang kwarta, ang pera, ay ang cheque, nag
Gina F. Acosta: -inform po ang aking head of agency na i-release ko po sa aming security officer. So while on the way na po ako papuntang office, I called up the security officer informing him
Gina F. Acosta: na
Gina F. Acosta: na-encash ko na po ang
Gina F. Acosta: cheque.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: You inform the security officer?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, ma'am.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Can you please mention the name of the security officer? Si Colonel Nolasco din ho ba yan?
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po, ma'am. Sino po yan? Si Colonel Lachica po. Colonel Lachica. Can you please
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: enlighten the committee? Sino po ba si Colonel Lachica?
Gina F. Acosta: Si Colonel Lachica po ay siya po ang ground commander ng aming BPSBGs na na-assign po sa office of the Vice President.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Okay. So you informed Colonel La Chica that you have encashed already the cheque.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, ma'am.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: How about the physical handing of the money? Kailan po nangyari yan?
Gina F. Acosta: December 20 din po.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Magkano po ang binigay niyo kay Colonel La Chica?
Gina F. Acosta: Binigay ko po sa kanya lahat ang 125 million po. At saan po dinala
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: ni Colonel La Chica?
Gina F. Acosta: Yan ang hindi ko naalam, ma
Gina F. Acosta: 'am.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Sandali lang po. Anong oras po ba kayo nakabalik sa OVP?
Gina F. Acosta: Mga around
Gina F. Acosta: 4, 4pm.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: How long did it take you?
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: I think that's it, counsel.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Okay.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Let's go to next video for this point, Your Honor, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That is, can we show it?
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: You
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: were able to check if the items and the amounts provided in the object of expenditure total to 125 million. You checked that?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, ma'am.
Rep. Gerville “Jinky Bitrics” R. Luistro: Okay. Tanong Ms. Acosta, what gave you the confidence? Ano ang nagbigay sa inyo ng lakas ng loob na ibigay ang buong 125 million?
Gina F. Acosta: May
Gina F. Acosta: approval po kay Ma'am Inday Sara.
Gina F. Acosta: Hindi po. Yes po.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Page 137 of the TSN marked as PI-1G for the prosecution, please.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: will be the last item for this afternoon for the prosecution. Do you
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: trust Colonel La Chica, Representative Luistro? Acosta, I trust La Chica. I trust La Chica kasi ginatrust po siya ng aking head of office in Dysara. Representative Luistro, in other words, the only reason Why you're giving your trust to Col. La Chica is because of the instruction of the Vice President. Ms. Acosta, yes ma'am. Luistro, tama mo ba? Acosta, yes ma'am. Luistro, without the instruction of the Vice President, you will never give the entire amount of the 125 billion pesos to Col. La Chica. Ms. Acosta, what was your answer to that question?
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, sir.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: Basahin mo.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes, ma'am.
Atty. Amando Virgil D. Ligutan: That will be all for the prosecution this afternoon. But you will still continue with your direct tomorrow, counsel. Yes, Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thereafter, we will proceed with the cross of counsel for respondent.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Ma'am Gina, pansamantala po konyong pagpapaliban yung inyong testimonya. Balik po kayo bukas, ha? Opo, Your
Gina F. Acosta: Honor. Kung
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: maaari po, yan ang nasa visa pa rin ng parehong sabi ng inisyo po namin para po hanggang sa bukas. Para ipagpatuloy po niyo inyong testimonya sa kukumang ito.
Gina F. Acosta: Yes,
Gina F. Acosta: Your Honor.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Thank
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: you, ma'am. Your excuse, ma'am. Pwede na po kayong bumaba sa witness stand. Just for some administrative matters, the court takes... The court, rather, is in receipt of a 13 August letter of Mr. Lemuel Ortonio asking for leave or to be excused from attending the hearing this week because he is going to take a scheduled psychologist licensure exam administered by the PRC. Given that we are not yet through with Ms. Gina Acosta, we still have witness Eduarda
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Eduardo Fajarda.
Sen. Francis "Chiz" G. Escudero: Court finding merit in the request and good faith on the part of Ortonio, hereby grants the request of Mr. Ortonio so that he can take his licensure exam this week. The court will however inform him in advance that we will be issuing a subpoena for him to attend this hearing on Monday after he shall have taken his licensure exam. And a second matter. For the information of the senator-judges and the parties, the Clerk of Court has completed the comparison of the acknowledgement receipts marked as exhibits by both parties. Based on the acknowledgement receipts so far submitted, it appears that there are 3,616 common acknowledgement receipts, 2,666 pertaining to the Office of the Vice President, and 950 pertaining to the DepEd. All ARs are marked by the counsel for the respondent have corresponding ARs from the panel of prosecutors. We note, however, that out of the total of 4,492 acknowledgement receipts of the prosecution, 876 have no counterpart acknowledgement receipts from the respondent. We shall be furnishing both parties with a copy of the Clerk of Court's findings as well as the senator-judges for your information and reference. Forgive us given the inclement weather. We will be adjourning session early in the Senate also by instruction of the Senate President. That's why we're adjourning trial again also a bit earlier today. We will see you tomorrow unless trial is cancelled or unless session is cancelled due to inclement weather. For the meantime, there'll be no other business to be taken up. Trial is hereby adjourned until tomorrow, October 18, rather August 18 at 10 o'clock in the morning.